<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our sauiours iourney to the Gadarens: or the loue of Christ vnto man. Written by I. Iones Bachelour in Diuinity, and parson of S. Nicholas Acons, London</title>
            <author>Jones, John, 1574 or 5-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102837</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838599</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2983</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2983)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Our sauiours iourney to the Gadarens: or the loue of Christ vnto man. Written by I. Iones Bachelour in Diuinity, and parson of S. Nicholas Acons, London</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, 1574 or 5-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Henry Bel, and are to bee sold at his shop hard without Bishops-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Christs loue to man.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2983:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2983:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OVR SAVIOVRS IOVRNEY TO the Gadarens: <hi>OR</hi> The loue of Chriſt <hi>vnto Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by I. IONES Bachelour in Diuinity, and Parſon of S. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Acons, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 8.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lord what is man, that thou art ſo mindfull of him or the ſonne of man that thou ſo viſiteſt him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> for <hi>Henry Bel,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop hard without Biſhops-gate. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2983:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2983:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL THE TWO <hi>EQVALL SISTERS, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>
               </hi> R. Io. <hi>and M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>
               </hi> I. Vaſſ. Iohn Iones <hi>their ſonne, wiſheth increaſe</hi> of grace in this world and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation in the <hi>world to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST deere and louing Mothers, the Preachers note in the 12 of his <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes,</hi> and the 12 verſe, againſt the ſcribling Age wherein we liue, <hi>That there is no end of making of Bookes,</hi> had once made me vow my life to obſcuritie: yet ſuch you ſee, hath been the efficacie of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, that (for your ſakes) that which I meant moſt priuate vnto
<pb facs="tcp:2983:3"/>
my ſelfe, I haue now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated to the world. Your intreaties haue preuailed with me, and at the laſt you haue what long you haue deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. It is part of my prayers, that now you haue it, it may ſatisfie the leaſt part of your expectations. The aboundance of your loues (I confeſſe) at the firſt made you both to wiſh wel vnto me; and the deſire of ſeeing ſomewhat for your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, hath made you more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate vpon me: but thus far I haue bene wary to my ſelfe, though that imitating of the prodigall Gallants of theſe our times, I haue taken vp of you good large ſummes, and do pay you here againe with inke and paper: this is the onely coine you are like to receiue of me for your manifold charges beſtowed vpon me. Accept it then (I beſeech you) kindly, and caſt a look vpon it now and then: ſo perhappes you may
<pb facs="tcp:2983:3"/>
thinke at the laſt, that though your ſonne hath miſ-ſpent much, yet he hath not vtterly loſt all his time. It is yours now: for I haue ſealed &amp; deliuered it vp for your vſes; and ſooner you ſhould haue had it, but that ſome mens fingers, who haue delighted in theft, by chance, haue ſtolen Diuinitie from the Printer to make them good. If they make that vſe of it, I am glad they haue it: if to make vſe of other mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours they ſtole it from him, this Copy will witneſſe the worke is none of theirs: and I would haue them know, <hi>He ſeldome proues good that is growne old in theft and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</hi> But you to whom it doth belong, take it, and vſe it as your owne, and command me, who doth deſire to be imploied by you, in all offices of loue and duty. The God of loue, who giues to all abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vpbraideth none, fill you
<pb facs="tcp:2983:4"/>
both full of all ſpirituall bleſſings; that as louingly you haue liued here, and haue beene beloued, ſo aboue, when this life ſhal leaue you both, you may liue with the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of loue. <hi>Amen. London</hi> this 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March.</hi> 1615.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing and obedient ſonne, J. Iones.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2983:4"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL <hi>THE PARISHIONERS OF</hi> S. <hi>Nicholas Acons, I. Iones</hi> wiſheth all happineſſe in this life, and in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipfull and beloued my pariſhioners, hauing found out God-mothers for this infant of mine, it remaines now, that I intreate you all at once to play the God-fathers part for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of it. And ſo much the rather I intreate you, and hope you will be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, aboue others, to performe this duty, becauſe you, beſt of all others, know the birth of it, being conceiued and brought forth eſpecially for your ſakes: the originall being Sermons which I preached here amongſt you; and you I hope ſomwhat haue profited by them. The law prouides, that where the childe is borne, there (be it neuer
<pb facs="tcp:2983:5"/>
ſo baſe) it ſhould be kept, and you muſt foſter what is hatched amongſt you. Accept then kindly what is kindly meant towards you, and continue to loue him whoſe prayer is for you all to loue one another. Almightie God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his loue towards you, and cauſe you, that as you are ioyned together in friendly neighbour-hood, ſo you may be ioyned in heartie affection one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other: ſo that when this life ſhall haue end, as you haue liued and loued together here, ſo you may all ioyne with the reſt of the heauenly quire in ſinging louely hymnes vnto the God of loue. And in that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I take my leaue, and commit you all to his protection, who for his power is able, and for his exceeding loue, wil keepe you all in the bond of loue. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well. From my houſe in S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> lane, this ninth of March. <hi>1615.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very louing and kind Friend:</hi> I. Iones.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2983:5"/>
            <head>CHRISTS LOVE TO MAN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE. 8.22.23.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>22.</hi>
                     </bibl> Now it came to paſſe on a certaine day, that he went into a ſhip, with his Diſciples: and he ſayd vnto them, Let vs go ouer vnto the other ſide of the Lake, and they lanched forth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>23.</hi>
                     </bibl> But as they ſailed, hee fell aſleepe, and there came downe a ſtorme of winde on the lake, and they were filled with water, &amp; were in ieopardy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>24.</hi>
                     </bibl> And they came to him, and awoke him, ſaying; Maiſter, Maiſter, we periſh. Then hee aroſe and rebuked the winde, and the raging of the water: and they ceaſed, and there was a calme.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words (beloued) of the Euangeliſt, now read vnto you, containe in them, the iourney of our Sauiour vnto the <hi>Gada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> and in the iourney a mighty mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2983:6"/>
he went vnto the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, the <hi>Epitome</hi> and <hi>Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> of all mankinde; men, that were more inly touched with the loſſe of their hogges, then with the ſinnes of their ſoules, the true picture of couetous man, who ſo conformes himſelfe vnto his wealth, as that he accounts his life, his ſoule, his bliſſe, his good: tell him of his ſoule, and the torments of hell, he ſtands and ſtares you in the face, and knowes not what your ſpeech doth meane; touch but his hogge, and the whole Countrey of the <hi>Gadarens</hi> will ſuddenly be vp in Armes together againſt you: yet thither he goes, that ſo they themſelues, might be witneſſes againſt themſelues, of their owne deſerued and wilfull deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But in this iourney there falles out a miracle; a miracle, I ſay, both to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment and the confirmation of his Diſciples: to the aſtoniſhment; for they mutter amongſt themſelues, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man is this, for he commandeth both the windes and the water, and they obey him: to their confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, that by confirming all his ſeuerall doctrines
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2983:6"/>
with ſundry miracles, they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that hee was the true and onely Meſſias, that was ſent into the world, to be the ſaluation and rdemption of it.</p>
            <p>So then in theſe words, wee haue three parts to bee inquired into, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the three ſeuerall verſes here, euery verſe hath his particular part. The preparation for the iourney, the manner of the iourney, the miracle in the iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The preparation in the firſt verſe.</item>
               <item>2 The manner in the next verſe.</item>
               <item>3 The miracle in the laſt verſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And euery part hath his particular bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: there are foure in the firſt verſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The time.</item>
               <item>2 The meanes.</item>
               <item>3 His exhortation.</item>
               <item>4 Their obedience.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The time; <hi>Now it came to paſſe on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The meanes; <hi>That he went into a ſhip with his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His exhortation; <hi>And hee ſaid vnto them, Let vs go ouer vnto the other ſide of the lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2983:7"/>Their obedience: <hi>And they lunched forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond verſe there are foure things alſo.</p>
            <p>The manner of their trauell, and the accidents that fell out in their iourney, which be in number three.</p>
            <p>The manner of their trauell, they ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: <hi>But as they ſailed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The accidents they be three.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>He fell aſleepe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>And there came downe a ſtorme of winde on the lake.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>And they were filled with water, and were in ieopardy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the third verſe there are two things; the feare of the Diſciples, the power and authority of the Maiſter.</p>
            <p>The feare of the Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>And they came to him and awaked him, ſaying, Maiſter, maiſter, wee periſh.</hi> The power &amp; authority of the Maiſter:</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Then he aroſe, and rebuked the winds, and the raging of the waters: and they cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and there was a calme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now it came to paſſe on a certaine day, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word here, <hi>Now,</hi> it does not poynt vs out vnto any certaine time, as in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2983:7"/>
other places of the Scripture it does, as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 6. <hi>Nunc videbis, quae facturus ſum.</hi> The Lord intending for to worke his wonders in the land of Egypt, hee ſayes to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 6.1</note> 
               <hi>Now thou ſhalt ſee what I will do to Pharaoh.</hi> So <hi>Balac</hi> the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> deſirous for to ridde himſelfe of his dangerous neighbours the Iſraelites, in <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. hee ſends for <hi>Balaam</hi> the Southſayer, to come in all haſte vnto him, <hi>Nunc igitur veni &amp; maledic,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 22.6</note> 
               <hi>Come now therefore, I pray thee, come, and curſe me this people, for they are too mighty and too ſtrong for me.</hi> So old <hi>Simeon</hi> deſirous to be diſſolued, &amp; to be with the Lord, he ioyfully ſings his <hi>Nunc dimittis</hi> vnto the world:<note place="margin">Luk. 2.29.</note> 
               <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant depart in peace, &amp;c.</hi> So our Sauiour feeling of his death approching, he cries vnto his Father, <hi>Nunc ad to vento,</hi> now I come vnto thee: But heere this word <hi>Now</hi> it is not, as in thoſe places, an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe of time, but a Coniunction copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue, and ſignifies as much as <hi>Et,</hi> or <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> and ſo the Latine Tranſlation reades it: <hi>Factum est autem, in vna die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Now it came to paſſe on a certaine day,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2983:8"/>
that is, and it came to paſſe on a certaine day.</p>
            <p>The time is ſet downe in the follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing words; Now it came to paſſe on a <hi>certaine</hi> day, there is the time ſet downe; but what day that day was of the week, perhappes might bee thought to bee, both curious to enquire, and ouer-dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult alſo to be found out: he was ſent forth into the world to doe his fathers buſineſſe, and ſo earneſt was hee, in this Calling of his, that as the Tragedian ſpeakes in another ſence; <hi>Finis vnius gradus eſt futurs,</hi> the end of one buſines, was but the beginning of another; and as the Mathematitian ſaid, of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of that Art, <hi>Nulla dies ſine linea,</hi> no day ſhould paſſe ouer his head, without the drawing of a line more: ſo wee may ſafely ſay of our Sauiour, that no day paſſed ouer his head, in which hee did not make profeſſion of the Goſpell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people: for hee profeſſeth this of himſelfe, that in it, he tooke his ſole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. <hi>My meate</hi> (ſayes hee) <hi>is to do the will of him that ſent me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>and to finiſh his worke.</hi> And ſo hauing finiſhed what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2983:8"/>
buſineſſe was conuenient, amongſt his owne people, the next day after perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, ſet forward for this intended iourney of his, without ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of the day at all, and ſo <hi>It came to paſſe on a certaine day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To keepe a <hi>Diarie</hi> of euery dayes work of his, it had bin a labour infinit, ſo many, ſo diuers were the miracles, that were wrought by him daily, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> teſtifies of him in his 21 chapter, it had been endleſſe: For (ſayes hee) <hi>there are many other things, which Ieſus did,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.25.</note> 
               <hi>the which if they ſhould be written, euery one, I ſuppoſe that euen the world it ſelfe could not containe the bookes that ſhould be written;</hi> and therefore no Regiſter being kept of them, they are poaſted ouer vnto cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dayes. <hi>Now it came to paſſe on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſome probable coniecture might bee giuen of the day, though no defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſentence, to conclude it abſolute: The Latine and the Greeke tranſlations they giue vs a little glimmering light of this ſame day, for they both reade it the ſelfe ſame way, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſayes the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2983:9"/>
Greeke text; and the Latine text, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt autem in vna dierum,</hi> and it came to paſſe in one of the dayes: Now both the Greeke and the Latine tongue, doe often reckon <hi>One</hi> for <hi>Firſt,</hi> as likewiſe many times does our Engliſh Dialect, one, two, three, that is, firſt, ſecond, third, &amp;c. And the Hebrues, they haue no other word, to expreſſe their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in: and therefore whereas we read it in our Engliſh Tranſlation, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and the euening and the morning were the firſt day,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.5.</note> the Hebrue Tranſlation reades it;<note place="margin">Haggi. 1.1</note> the euening and the morning were one day. So likewiſe in <hi>Haggai</hi> 1. where we reade it, in the firſt day of the moneth, came the word of the Lord: they ſay, in the <hi>one</hi> day of the moneth, came the word of the Lord, hauing no other word to expreſſe their meaning. And the Latine, and the Greeke, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing of the Hebrue phraſe, for the <hi>Firſt</hi> ſay <hi>one,</hi> as in <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Mark. 16.2</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Sabbathorum,</hi> where our Tranſlation reades it, and very earely in the morning, the firſt day of the weeke, they came vnto the Sepulchre, &amp;c. So
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2983:9"/>
here it is ſet downe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one day, which day, may very well ſignifie, the firſt day, and that is this day.</p>
            <p>But if it were this day, how comes it then to paſſe (it may well be demanded) that our Sauiour is guilty of the breach of that commandement, <hi>Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabboth day, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>in it, thou ſhalt doe no manner of worke, &amp;c.</hi> which was ſo ſtrictly obſerued amongſt the Iewes, as that in the 12. of <hi>Mathew</hi> the Diſciples are reprehended by the Phariſes, for but plucking of the eares of Corne on the Sabboth day;<note place="margin">Math. 12.2</note> 
               <hi>Behold thy Diſciples, they doe that which is not lawfull to doe on the Sabboth day.</hi> If it were not lawfull for them to plucke a fewe eares of Corne on the Sabboth day, then ſurely, much leſſe was it lawfull for them to take their iourney on the Sabboth day.</p>
            <p>Yes verily, euen on the Sabboth day, it was lawfull for them to trauell, though not to make any long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on the Sabboth day, and therefore in the Acts. 1,<note place="margin">Acts. 1.12.</note> Mount <hi>Oliuet</hi> is ſayd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2983:10"/>
to bee from Ieruſalem a Sabboth dayes iourney: which Sabboth dayes iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney contained in it, as the writers do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vpon it, two miles in diſtance, the which it was lawfull for them to walke on the Sabboth day; and therefore in the place before cited, in the 12. of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.1.</note> the Diſciples were not found fault with, by the Phariſes, for that they trauelled on the Sabboth day, but for that they pluckt the eares of corne on the Sabboth day. But yet it may bee demanded further (for wee are fallen into a labyrinth of queſtions) how comes this permiſſion of a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both dayes iourney, ſeeing all iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the law, is expreſſely forbidden. <hi>See,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 16.29</note> ſayes <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. <hi>See,</hi> ſayes hee, <hi>for that the Lord hath giuen you the Sabboth, therefore he giueth you on the ſixt day, the bread of two dayes, abide yee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery man in his place, let no no man go out of his place on the ſeuenth day.</hi> If euery man were commanded to abide in his place, on the ſeuenth day, how then comes in this Sabboth dayes iourney?</p>
            <p>Why certainly, I can giue no other
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2983:10"/>
reaſon for it, but what <hi>Oecumenius</hi> and <hi>Lorinus</hi> doe giue, and that is, that in the time of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it to bee proclaimed, that the Arke going before, there ſhould be a diſtance left between it &amp; the campe, of two thouſand cubites, by meaſure, as as it is <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 3.3.</note> which was the iuſt diſtance of two miles, whither it was lawfull for the people for to go, to viſite the Arke, euen on the Sabboth day, and ſo may come in our Sabboth daies iourney.</p>
            <p>But yet wee are not thus quite of our queſtion though, for ſtill it may be vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged further, that this was more then a Sabboth daies iourney, for it was aboue two miles that he was to trauell:<note place="margin">Mat. 4.18. Luke 5.1. Ioſh. 6.1.</note> Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> calles it in his 4 chap. <hi>the ſea of Galilee:</hi> S. <hi>Luke</hi> in his 5. chapt. <hi>the lake of Geneſareth:</hi> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his 6. chapt. <hi>the ſea of Tiberias:</hi> a broad and large place, ſo that howſoeuer, he was ſtill without the compaſſe of two thouſand cubites, his Sabboth dayes iourney: how may this bee?</p>
            <p>For this we ſay, that our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> he did not iourney on the Sabboth day,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2983:11"/>
for the Iewes Sabboth, it was our Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday, and that was the ſeuenth day: but this was the firſt day, afterwards changed by the Apoſtles, in memory of our Sauiours moſt glorious reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who dyed vpon the Friday, and roſe againe the third day, which was Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and therefore by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his firſt of his <hi>Apoc.</hi> is called <hi>Dies Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 1.10.</note> the Lords day: <hi>I was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the ſpirit on the Lords day;</hi> that part then of the Commandement the <hi>Sabboth day,</hi> it was but Ceremoniall, not Morall; for had it beene Morall, it had bound vs, perpetually, to the obſeruation of it; but wee ſee it was altered, and continues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered vnto this day; and ſo wee haue a geſſe of the time, which is here ſet down indefinitely, <hi>a certaine day,</hi> though no definitue ſentence to conclude it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory: <hi>Now it came to paſſe on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It came to paſſe;</hi> Heere haue our licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Epicures, and our vpſtart Atheiſts, a ground &amp; foundation (as they thinke) to build vp their Chance-medly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in the world; that things they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2983:11"/>
come by chance and fortune, not by the determinate, and deliberate prouidence and diſpoſing of the Almighty, For what greater argument of chance, can there be, ſay they, then that <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſhould in his owne buſineſſe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a caſualty, for the Text is plaine: <hi>Now it came to paſſe,</hi> or it chanced, <hi>on a certaine day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But their foundation, it is laid but on a ſandy ground, for <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> long ſince, though but a Heathen Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, yet he could ſay, by the twy-light of nature, that <hi>ignorantia cauſarum,</hi> the ignorance of man was that, that made blind fortune a goddeſſe amongſt men: for when they ſaw no reaſon for many things that came to paſſe amongſt them, they did not conceiue, that there might be a reaſon which they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues did not ſee, but ſtraight way they deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fortune, &amp; made her the author and beſtower of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all vpon the world, her that is ſo brittle a goddeſſe, <hi>quae cum ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det frangitur,</hi> which is daſhed in peeces by the leaſt accident; whereas our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſts rule is quite contrary, for he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2983:12"/>
teacheth vs another doctrine in the tenth of Saint <hi>Mathewes</hi> Goſpell,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.29</note> for hee makes Prouidence reach vnto the ſmalleſt matters, euen vnto the falling of a Sparrow vpon the ground: <hi>Are there not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>two Sparrowes ſold for a farthing, and yet one of them ſhall not fall on the ground, without the will of your heauenly Father:</hi> Then much more the weightieſt matters, ſuch as the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell is, which is the ſaluation of the ſoule of man, that ſhall not be done, but by a particular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence indeed, and that iourney reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on with mature deliberation.</p>
            <p>Fortune (as the world eſteemes it) it is but an Idoll, made for fooliſh man to worſhip and adore, and he that will worſhip any thing, euen the meaneſt of creatures, will not neglect it, wherein hee thinkes hee ſees ſome ſhew, but as it is indeed in it owne nature, it is <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria poteſtas Dei,</hi> the ordinary proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and direction of Almighty God himſelfe, by which he brings to paſſe, what himſelfe intendeth.</p>
            <p>This iourney here of our Sauiours, it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2983:12"/>
is vndertaken with a ſingular reſolution to do good vnto all, euen thoſe that were moſt wicked and prophane: So is it Gods goodneſſe for to ſuper-abound, where the ſinne of man ſeemes for to abound. The heart of man for his wickedneſſe it is termed in Scripture <hi>Abyſſus,</hi> a bottomeleſſe pit, according to that of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in the 17. of his Prophecy.<note place="margin">Eze. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>Prauum eſt cor hominis &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrutabile, &amp; quis cognoſcet:</hi> The heart of man it is vnſearchable, and who ſhall know it? yet the mercy and goodneſſe of God, it is farre deeper then that, that is ſo deepe, as that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 11. to the <hi>Romanes</hi> is faine to cry out: <hi>O altitudo diuitiarum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.33</note> Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſedome and knowledge of God: And in regard of his mercies, he is termed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Pater miſericor diarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.2</note> the Father, not of one or two, but of many mercies, and the God of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he is called the Father of mercies, to pardon all the ſinnes that man ſhall commit againſt him, and the Apoſtle in the <hi>Epheſians</hi> tels vs,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.7.</note> that when we ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2983:13"/>
need them, he has, <hi>abundantet diuitia: gratia,</hi> exceeding riches of his grace, in ſtore for vs, if we our ſelues will but willingly accept, what he ſhall kindly offer vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Hee does not take this iourney heere vpon him, vpon a giddy humour, but a diſcreete deliberation, to go vnto them; and becauſe he did go, therefore here it is ſaid; it came to paſſe: <hi>Factum eſt,</hi> ſaies the Latine Text, it was done, ſo it came to paſſe. <hi>Now it came to paſſe on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing followes, the meanes, he went into a Ship with his Diſciples: <hi>Now it came to paſſe on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day, that hee entred into a Ship with his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Mac. 4.9.</note>It is the ſpeech of <hi>Iudas Maeccabaeus,</hi> 1. Mac. 4. that when he was to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his Army againſt <hi>Gorgias</hi> his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, he wils them not to feare their multitude, nor to be afraid of their aſſault: <hi>mementate,</hi> ſayes hee, <hi>qualiter facti ſunt ſalui patres noſtri,</hi> Remember ſayes he, how our fathers were ſaued in the red Sea, when <hi>Pharoah</hi> purſued
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2983:13"/>
them with an Army; if euer we ſhould be mindefull of any thing, then this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular we ſhould not forget.</p>
            <p>Heere wee haue an example in this ſame Story of our fore-fathers, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, how they, and we in them, were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, from the danger of a tempeſt. After that our Euangeliſt had ſhewed what miracles our Sauiour had acted on the the Land, he ſets downe now, as great a miracle as any of the reſt, that hee did vpon the Sea, that ſo both earth and Sea might witneſſe with him, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and truth of the doctrine that hee Preached to the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now it came to paſſe, on a certaine day, that he went into a Ship, with his Diſciples.</hi> He went into a Ship: Why what need now had he more of a Ship, then at any time elſe we read he had? Was not hee the Lord and God of the water, as well as of the Land, and could hee not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the one as well as the other? Was not this hee, that for his peoples ſake, dried vp the red ſea, and made them to go through as vpon dry land? <hi>Exod.</hi> 14,<note place="margin">Ex. 14.22.</note> Is not this the ſame, that when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2983:14"/>
him, walked vpon the water as vpon firme ground,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.29.</note> and made his Diſciple <hi>Peter</hi> tread there alſo? <hi>Mat.</hi> 14. Why then but for the paſſage ouer of a little Lake, would he haue a Ship for to ferry him ouer? could hee go vpon the Sea when it was boyſterous and rough, and muſt he be paſſed ouer a Lake, when it is calme and quiet? what meanes this paſſage of his that he went into a Ship?</p>
            <p>Yes (Beloued) he could haue done it as well without a Ship as within the Ship, had it pleaſed him, but hee ſaw it more conuenient for him for to do it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: Hee could haue either dryed the Lake with his word, as hee did the red Sea, or haue walked vpon it at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as at other times he did, but heere hee would neither of theſe, hee would chooſe rather, to go as a paſſenger, then as a Lord and Commander of what was his owne.</p>
            <p>To dry the Sea with his word, or walke vpon it at his pleaſure, were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and tokens of his Diuinity, but heere he would be knowne to be a naturall man, he came into the world to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2983:14"/>
take vpon him our infirmities, and to cure vs by thoſe, who long before were wounded vnto death, bee was our Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and we all his Patients; now a Phyſition that cannot skill of his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents infirmities, ſhall hardly be able to cure thoſe diſeaſes, and how ſhall he be better skilled in our wants, then by fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them himſelfe? hee would feele our wants in this, as well as beare our infirmities in other matters: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay</hi> tels vs what he hath done for vs in other matters, in the 53 of his Prophecy, where he ſayes:<note place="margin">Eſay 53.4.</note> 
               <hi>Surely he hath borne of our griefes, and carryed our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; he was wounded for our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by his ſtripes, were we healed:</hi> So heere hee would know our wantes, in being paſſenger in a Fiſhers Ketch.</p>
            <p>Had our Sauiour remained God alone, as he was at the firſt, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort on benefite had that bene vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and or if he had taken humane fleſh vpon him, and not taken our infirmities withall, he could not haue beene ſeene ſo well in mans miſeries as he was; but therefore he tooke them that he might
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2983:15"/>
be well skilled in them, and being skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in them, hee might compaſſionate them, and compaſſionating of them he might throughly cure &amp; heale them all.</p>
            <p>In this one iourney then of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, he did ſuch things as might truely ſhew he was truely man, and withall he might demonſtrate himſelfe to bee the Son of the euerliuing God. He went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſhip &amp; ſlept, that by both he might inſtruct vs of the want of neceſſaries, that bee in our nature, hee rebuked the wind and appeaſed the Sea, that ſo he might ſhew vs the power of his Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>He went into a Ship:</hi> but not into the <hi>warſpite,</hi> no man of war to do miſchiefe withall, for though himſelfe were come as himſelfe profeſſes,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.49.</note> in <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>I am come to ſend fire vpon the earth, and what is my deſire but that it were already kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled;</hi> yet he would not, as our Pirates now adaies do, fetch his fire from hel to blow men quick vp into heauen, that he hath left for thoſe diueliſh helhounds, without their greater repentance, that as they haue ſerued others, ſo they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues at the laſt ſhold be ſerued, blown
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2983:15"/>
vp with fire here, and perpetually after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be burnt in euerlaſting fire: But he went into a poore Fiſhers ſhip, a ſhip of trade and labour, that ſo all things might anſwere in proportion both his birth, life, and death, all ſhould bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable one vnto the other.</p>
            <p>His birth it was poore and needy, a Village for the place, an Inne for his houſe, a Stable for his chamber, a cratch for his bed: what poore beggar amongſt men, more miſerably borne? <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in Scripture is proclaimed to be the Citty of the great King, &amp; what King greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this King of ours, who hath both on his veſture &amp; on his thigh a name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Rex regum &amp; Dominus dominantium, King of Kings and Lord of Lords:</hi> yet this great Lord will chooſe rather to honor with his birth, little <hi>Bethlem</hi> the leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the thouſands of <hi>Iudah,</hi> then fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the Metropolis of the world, litle <hi>Bethle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> I ſay, ſhal be honored by his birth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> famous <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall diſhonor her ſelf, by his death &amp; paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>In this ſmall village of <hi>Bethlem,</hi> he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commands Princely Pallaces, nor
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2983:16"/>
great mans houſe, but contents himſelfe to bee borne, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> ſpeakes, in a baſe, and a common Inne, a place made for the receipt of the meaneſt company, and in that Inne hee takes vp a Stable for his Nurſery, and a Cratch for his chaire of Eſtate, a poore Carpenter and his wife for his priuy Counſellours, an Oxe and an Aſſe for his common Courtiers, thus the mighty God, whoſe Seate is in heauen, and the earth is his Foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, muſt bee contented with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt place that vaine man can finde out for him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaies <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Thus he that makes all other men rich, himſelfe muſt be borne like a beggar in ſome out roome; and he that is full of all ſpirituall bleſſings, muſt be as one who were voyde of all.</p>
            <p>His life is proportionable vnto his birth, hee is driuen into baniſhment ſo ſoone as he is borne, and afterwards, aboue the courſe of nature, he is forced to faſt forty daies and forty nights, heb is ſcoffed at by his kindred, reuiled by the Gouernours, curſed by the Doctors;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2983:16"/>
called Coniurer by the Commons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by his ſeruants, ſcorned by the Courtiers, mocked by the Souldiers, rayled at by the Malefactors, his whole life was nothing elſe but a map of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries; wandring vp and down he goes, not hauing where to repoſe his wearied limbes. <hi>Math.</hi> 8. <hi>The Foxes haue holes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; the Birdes haue neſts, but the Son of man hath not whereon to reſt his head:</hi> The wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe is faine to be his Couch, and a few poore Fiſhermen his guard to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon him; his prouiſion is fiue bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley loaues, and two ſmall fiſhes, and what are they amongſt ſo many? Ferri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ouer here, he is, in a poore fiſhermans boate, the vileſt and moſt contemptible of all other Trades. But his comming it was in humility, and therefore hee contents himſelf with the baſeſt things; he, <hi>Whoſe the ſea is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.5.</note> 
               <hi>and whoſe hands pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the dry lands, Pſal.</hi> 95. Hee (I ſay) is mad paſſenger in a Ketch, in a poore Fiſher-boate, ferried ouer to the other ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He went into a ſhip,</hi> but he went not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, hee was accompanied with his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2983:17"/>
Diſciples, <hi>He went into a ſhip</hi> (ſaies my Text) <hi>with his Diſciples,</hi> hee went with his Diſciples, that ſo he might proue their faith vpon the ſea, as well as vpon the ſolide and dry land, euery way hee would try them, that ſo hee might har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them againſt the time of affliction. Almighty God, though he knew <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> throughly, yet he would try him in the weightieſt matter, to ſee whether hee would remaine conſtant vnto the end;<note place="margin">Gen. 22.2.</note> as you may reade at large in the twenty two Chapter of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> Go offer vp thy ſonne <hi>Iſaac</hi> vpon one of the Mountaines that I ſhall tell thee of, who holding of Gods promiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, certaine and ſure, that in his ſeede all the Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, would rather truſt in what hee hoped for, then in what hee ſaw before his eyes; before his eyes hee ſaw nothing but certaine death, and yet aboue hope, hee hoped for nothing but euerlaſting life. <hi>Non haeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabat</hi> (ſaies Saint <hi>Auguſtine) quod ſibi reddi poterat immolatus, qui dari pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat non ſperatus,</hi> hee no more doubted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2983:17"/>
that his ſonne ſhould be reſtored vnto him, after he was ſacrificed, then hee doubted hee ſhould haue him before he had him.</p>
            <p>So our Sauiour here, hee would tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly try his Apoſtles in their conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in the neareſt matters, not in the death of their children and ſons, but in the death of their owne ſelues, he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all their liues at once to a manifeſt danger, hee carries them to ſea: hee goes into a ſhip, and his Diſciples with him.</p>
            <p>Wherein they ſhew themſelues true friends indeed, and faithfull ſeruants vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Maiſter, who will not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company him in his labours, but euen in imminent and manifeſt dangers, wil not forſake him: ſo that our Sauiour might well giue that teſtimony of them,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.28</note> that he does in the 22. of <hi>Luke, vos eſtis,</hi> yee are they which haue continued with me in my temptations.</p>
            <p>And to digreſſe a little from them, and turne the dyall vnto our ſelues, wee all know that Chriſt our Lord is much ſooner found in affliction &amp; tribulation,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2983:18"/>
then he is in mirth &amp; iollity: Chriſt, he is the Lilly; but as it is ſaid of the Lilly in the <hi>Canticles: Hee is growing amongſt the thornes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.2. Mat. 27.29</note> nay he is crowned with a crown of thornes, <hi>Math.</hi> 27. ſooner found in the houſe of mourning, then in the courts of ioy and gladneſſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> in the 3.<note place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note> of <hi>Exod.</hi> found him in the bramble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh,<note place="margin">1. King. 19.4.</note> when all the Egyptians miſſed him in their court. <hi>Elias</hi> in 1. <hi>King.</hi> enioyed him vnder the Iuniper tree, a tree full of prickes, when <hi>Ahab</hi> could not intreate him in his ſeeled pallaces.</p>
            <p>But yet the world is in a contrary veine, quite from this, they will follow Chriſt, in proſperity, but in aduerſity they will giue him leaue to bee alone: vpon the land he ſhall haue followers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, why hee hath whole multitudes attending on him, <hi>Ecce totus mundus,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Behold the whole world runs after him,</hi> but vpon the ſea, his traine hath left him, onely his Apoſtles they keepe him company; <hi>He went into a ſhip with his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt God rewardes men with his gifts, for the ſeruice they haue done him,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2983:18"/>
ſo long he ſhall haue followers enough, but if once their profeſſion beginne to draw blood, then <hi>Demas</hi> will reuolt, &amp; make ſhipwracke of all that before hee hath profeſſed: there are but a few that can indure this <hi>Baptiſmus ſanguinis,</hi> to dye their colours in graine, that ſo they may be knowne to be his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Theſe kind of men I cannot more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſemble, then vnto the vſurers of theſe our dayes, who will willingly lend their money vnto our merchants, but vpon this condition, that howſoeuer the world go with the poore merchant-aduenturer, the vſurer ſtill will bee ſure to be a gainer by him; ſo theſe they will follow Chriſt in his glory, where they may reape their priuate advantage, but by any meanes they will not endure to heare of him in his croſſe and paſſion: otherwiſe, farre otherwiſe was it with his Diſciples here, both in proſperity &amp; or aduerſity, they will be ſure to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with him, if their Lord will to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, then they will alongſt with him; <hi>He went into a ſhippe with his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might heere enter into a large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2983:19"/>
of our humane baſeneſſe, and our degenerate nature, how ready all of vs are to deny our Lord and Maiſter; but I liſt not ſhew that in words, which every one of vs do daily act in our doings: we follow Chriſt vnto the wedding, we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him our Maiſter in the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of bread, and we honor him high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the acting of miracles; but in perils, and in dangers, in loſſes, and in death, we do deteſt him: In every one of theſe, wee ſet vp this for our Mott, <hi>Vos autem non ſic;</hi> farre, oh as farre as may bee, let the leaſt of all theſe be from vs, let them not once approach the place, where we ſhall dwell. For we are like vnto the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites in the 15 of <hi>Exodus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15.1</note> who when they ſaw their cruell enemies, the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> drowned before their faces, and they themſelues maiſters of the field, without ſo much as ſtriking of one ſtroke for it, they burſt out preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to cheerefull ſongs, <hi>Cantemus Domino,</hi> let vs ſing vnto the Lord, for hee hath triumphed gloriouſly, the Horſe and his Rider hath hee throwne into the Sea: but preſently after their proviſion fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2983:19"/>
them, in the very next chapter,<note place="margin">Exod. 16.3</note> 
               <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 16. they murmure againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and mutter againſt the Lord, and faine they would returne, to their Bricke-making in Egypt: ſo wee, whilſt hee beſtowes wealth, and riches, and glory, &amp; honor, and the like vpon vs, all that while, wee thinke wee haue gotten all with a ſong, wee ceaſe not to ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 81 <hi>Pſalme, Cantemus Domino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſing wee merrily vnto God our ſtrength, make a cheerfull noyſe vnto the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> all is well, and as we would haue it; but if hee once try vs with the touch-ſtone of aduerſity, if he make vs to go through fire and water, we ſuddenly change the coppy of our countenance, and in ſtead of giuing thankes, wee ſay with <hi>Iob</hi> in the third of that Booke,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Pereat dies in quae natus ſum, &amp; nox in quae dictum eſt, conceptus eſt homo,</hi> Let the day periſh wherein I was borne, and the night when it was ſayd, a Man childe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, let them follow that liſt, for wee for our owne parts haue enough of the ſeruice of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Chriſt our Sauiour, he hath farre more
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2983:20"/>
followers of his reſurrection, then of his paſſion, of his glory then of his troubles; but his Diſciples yet aboue all his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, they remained firme with him, and would not forſake him: <hi>Hee went into a ſhip with his Diſciples.</hi> And ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels them what they are to looke for in recompence againe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.7.</note> in 2. <hi>Cor. If they ſhall be partakers of his ſufferings, they ſhall bee partakers alſo of the conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour here, he carries his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples vnto the ſea, that ſo hee might trye them, in all kindes, before he ſent them forth, to harden them againſt all ſtormes of affliction that ſhould blowe, and to teach them to contemne the vanities of this world. In the world there are ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den alterations, &amp; he would haue them altered with none, he would haue them to be men of courage, and beare adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity as well as proſperity.</p>
            <p>Will you ſee the changes of the world? I will onely giue you one inſtance Act. 14. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14.11</note> at their firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e into <hi>Liſtra,</hi> they haue much a doe to containe the people from doing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto them, as Gods; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Gods,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2983:20"/>
ſay they, <hi>are come downe to vs in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men:</hi> whereas at the 19 verſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of the ſame chapter, for the good that <hi>Paul</hi> did amongſt them,<note place="margin">verſ. 19.</note> they ſtone him with ſtones, and throw him out of their Citty, a ſudden alteration: As great an alteration is this here, with the Diſciples; Our Sauiour he honors them with his company, he giues them power ouer vncleane ſpirits; but here hee tries them with the perill of their liues. <hi>Hee went into a ſhippe with his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee went firſt, his Diſciples followed after: the Maiſter hee muſt be the firſt, that muſt ſhew example vnto the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and what hee would haue his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler learne, that he muſt teach him by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as well as by precept. It is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Abimelech,</hi> a Prince and leader of Iſraell in <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.48.</note> that intending to burn <hi>Sichem,</hi> hee tooke an Axe in his hand, and cut downe a bough from a tree, and laid it vpon his owne ſhoulders, ſaying vnto his ſouldiers, <hi>Quod me vidistis fuce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> facite,</hi> what you haue ſeene mee doe, make haſte and doe the like, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them by example to do what he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2983:21"/>
would haue done; and certainly the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple will doe it much more willingly, when he ſees his Maiſter doe the ſame before his face: and if there be a maiſter in miſchiefe, he ſhall be able to do more hurt by his onely example, then a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of others by all the wholeſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts that they can reade: therefore if we be wiſe, let vs with <hi>Mary</hi> chooſe the better part, and ſo we ſhall be ſure to be profitable indeed.</p>
            <p>The third thing followes: his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; <hi>Let vs goe ouer to the other ſide of the lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The power of our Sauiour, as he was the Creator vnto his diſciples, and they his creatures, it was very great, what might he not haue commanded them to doe? he created them by his word, and therefore might haue commanded them by his word alſo, to hime executed and fulfilled the vtmoſt of his will: the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he may do as he liſt with his clay, &amp; no man to controll him, and God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as it pleaſeth him of man, and none to aske the queſtion, why hee doth ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee might haue ſayd vnto his Diſciples,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2983:21"/>
get you ouer vnto the other ſide of the lake, or follow me vnto the otherſide of the lake, and they were to obey: for he was their Lord, and they his ſeruants, he to command, and they to do him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; and in equity and iuſtice this hee might haue done, without any preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice at all vnto any one of them at all, euen the chiefeſt and beſt beloued.</p>
            <p>But yet ſuch is the loue of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that be his, and appertaine vnto him, as that he will do, he will euermore doe in loue and amity: he will not ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly command, but kindly intreate at their hands; <hi>Let vs go ouer vnto the other ſide of the lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia Dei, vinea Dei, grandis nimis,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> the Church of God ſayes he, it is Gods vineyard, great and high in the account of the Lord; and great reaſon indeed, is it (if we conſider it throughly as wee ought) that ſo it ſhould be; great, yea very great in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimate, who hath beſtowed ſuch coſt &amp; care continually about it, his own right hand hath planted it, his deere heart blood hath redeemed it, he hath watred
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2983:22"/>
it with his word, hee hath cauſed it to ſhoot forth by his grace, he hath made it plentifull and aboundant by his ſpirit, and can wee thinke that all this coſt of his, will not make him to haue a regard vnto it?</p>
            <p>Yes ſurely he hath both had, and at this day hath, ſo great a care ouer it, as that in the aboundance of his loue, hee hath married himſelfe vnto his Church, hee now is our husband, and the Church is his ſpouſe, and thinking with himſelfe, that, that vnity is too little for it, he hath moulded vs all into his owne body, ſo that now as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.30.</note> 
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. wee are the members of his body, of his fleſh &amp; of his bones, and therfore muſt needs loue vs with an exceeding loue: for it is the ſame S. <hi>Pauls</hi> note, in the ſame chapter, verſ. 29. that yet it was neuer heard, that euer any man hated his owne body, but nouriſhed and cheriſhed it, and therfore can do no leſſe then ſpeake kinde vnto it. <hi>Let vs go ouer, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence forward then, when we heare of Gods preſence, let vs not like our Grand-father <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradice, flye
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2983:22"/>
from the ſight of him, for it is his loue which makes him draw neere to vs, <hi>Noli fugero Adam,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> doe not ſayes he, oh man, flye from thy maker, he is nothing elſe but God with vs, be not afraid or terrified at the newes of him: for he is with vs in the fleſh, hee is with vs alſo in the vnity of the ſpirit, ſo that he cannot chooſe but loue vs eternally.</p>
            <p>Let not the ſight of our ſins ſo vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſmay vs, as that we ſhal think there is no more place left for grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine: for as S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs, that where ſinne aboundes,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.20</note> there grace aboundes much more, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. and Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> ſhewes vs the meanes, how Chriſt and the ſinner doe meete in one; <hi>Cor,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>eſt in peccatore, anima in corde, mens in anima, fi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in monte, Chriſtus in fide.</hi> In e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſinner there is a heart, in the heart there is a ſoule, in the ſoule there is a mind, in the mind there is faith, in faith there is Chriſt; and this is that, ſayes he, that the Apoſtle ſhewes, when he ſayes, <hi>that Chriſt dwels in your hearts by faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>When our Sauiours to furious Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2983:23"/>
               <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> wold haue had fire from heauen to conſume the company, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. <hi>Lord, wilt thou that we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand fire from heauen to conſume them there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 9.54.</note> 
               <hi>as Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as did?</hi> What was his anſwer? <hi>Yee know not of what ſpirit yee bee;</hi> they coſt him more then ſo, to confound them all in an inſtant, &amp; he had much rather bring them home vnto him in loue, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them in his anger: our Sauiour is of a more milde and quiet ſpirit then his Diſciples are of: for they ſought the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their neighbours, but God he ſeekes the conuerſion of ſinners.</p>
            <p>When God ſhewed himſelfe vnto <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> in the mount, there paſſed before him thunder and lightning, and ſtorme and wind, but God was in none of them all, but in the ſtil voice, he delights to be mercifull, and is loath to take reuenge, euen of thoſe that are his enemies: he is ſlow to take his bow in hand, more loath to bend it, loather yet to draw it, loather of all to let flye at his enemies: <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. <hi>Ah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>I wil eaſe me of mine enemies, and auenge mee of mine aduerſaries,</hi> as though he were ſo loath to do it, as that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2983:23"/>
it ſhould not be done, if the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by any other meanes could be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. If he be then ſo kinde vnto his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, no maruaile at all if hee ſpeake friendly vnto ſuch as are his friends: <hi>Let vs goe ouer to the other ſide of the lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet he is not more ready to aske, then they are ready for to obey, which is our fourth part, their Obedience, they lanched forth; <hi>Let vs goe ouer vnto the other ſide of the lake, and they lanched forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 11. of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell,<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.11.</note> when our Sauiour puts vp his requeſt vnto his Diſciples, to goe and raiſe his friend <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the dead, they refuſe to goe with him, <hi>Lord if hee ſleepe hee ſhall doe well,</hi> ſay they; but then they had not learned their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fully: but now they were like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Centurions ſeruant, in the 8. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> he can no ſooner ſay go,<note place="margin">Math. 8.9.</note> but they go; come, but they come; doe this, but they do it: no ſooner in the ſhip, and ſayes vnto them, let vs go ouer to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, but preſently in all obedience,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2983:24"/>
they lanch forth the veſſell; <hi>And they lanched forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This obedience of theirs is a triple twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted cord made of theſe three ſtrands, humility in the heart, patience in the mouth, and perſeuerance in all good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and of ſuch a cord the wiſe man ſayes, <hi>Funiculus triplex, &amp;c.</hi> a threefold cord is hardly broken: and euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of theſe they learned of their Lord and maiſter: for, for the firſt, humility in the heart,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.29</note> it is his owne ſpeech, in <hi>Math.</hi> 11. <hi>Diſcite à me quia mitis ſum,</hi> learne, ſayes he, of me, becauſe I am meeke and humble in heart, and yee ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules; for the ſecond, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the mouth, it is the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes</hi> ſpeech of him in his 53 Chapter:<note place="margin">Eſay 53.7.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut ouis ad occiſionem,</hi> hee was brought as a Lambe vnto the ſlaughter, and as a ſheepe before his ſhearer, ſo hee opened not his mouth; and for the third, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance in goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> it is the Apoſtles ſpeech, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>Obediens fuit vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> hee became obedient vnto death, euen the death of the croſſe: who could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more then he hath performed?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2983:24"/>And this obedience, as he had it here of his Apoſtles, ſo doth he expect it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo at the hands of euery one of vs that doe profeſſe our ſelues retainers vnto him, Humility, Patience, Perſeuerance, this is the beſt ſacrifice, and the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, which wee can performe vnto him; let vs all then ſtudy and indeuour ourſelues in the feare of the Lord, to learne this one leſſon, &amp; ſo, if not in this world, yet in the world to come, we are ſure we ſhall haue our reward, a reward I ſay, which ſhall continue with vs vnto all eternity; the which God grant vs all, <hi>Amen.</hi> And ſo we haue finiſhed the firſt verſe here, the ſecond followes. <hi>But as they ſailed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which, as I told you, there is ſet downe the manner of the iourney, and the accidents that befell them: the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the iourney, they ſayled, <hi>But as they ſailed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The manner of the Iourney, I ſhall not neede to ſtand long vpon it, it is knowne vnto all, <hi>they ſayled,</hi> and beſides their ſayling, they haue little other help to driue forward their moueable houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2983:25"/>The prophane Hiſtorians, in their Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, do aſcribe both the inuention of ſhipping, and the Art of Nauigation, vnto one of themſelues, to <hi>Atlas Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and make him both the inuenter, &amp; part perfecter of that ſecret Art; but we which are Chriſtians, we rather depend vpon the Scripture, and ſay, that the vſe of ſhipping, and the Art of Nauigation, they came both immediatly from God himſelfe, &amp; was firſt revealed vnto <hi>Noe,</hi> in the forme of the Arke, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the vſe of the Load-ſtone,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.13.</note> in theſe our later times, hath bin by Gods eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall prouidence, reuealed amongſt vs, without which the whole Ocean, as dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now it is, could not be made nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble either vnto vs, or any other people.</p>
            <p>The benefit of it is great, as we ſee dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by daily experience the tranſportati-of goods, the commutation of marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, with other nations, the which is ſo neceſſary amongſt men, that <hi>Baldus</hi> the great Lawyer, did not ſticke to affirme, the world would quickly be at an end, if Marchandizing once ſhould decay amongſt vs, and in Marchandizing,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2983:25"/>
the chiefeſt Trade we know is by ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and in ſhipping, ſayes <hi>Seneca,</hi> this one thing is none of the ſmalleſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Diuine Prouidence; <hi>Quod na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura dederit ventos, incitatores nauigatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, vt commoda cuiuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regionis, fierent communia:</hi> This is worthy of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion indeed, that God ſhould cauſe the winds to be furtherers of nauigation, by which the commodities of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are made knowne and common vnto one.</p>
            <p>This ſame ſayling in ſhips, it is called by the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the 107. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſ. 107.23.</note> 
               <hi>Deſcenſus in mare,</hi> a going downe into the Sea, for ſo he ſaith, thoſe that goe downe into the Sea in ſhips, they ſee the great wonders of the Lord; but this deſcent it is termed fo in reſpect of the ſhore onely, where the Bankes ſeeme higher then the waters doe, which are ſet as barres for it by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God himſelfe, which they ſhall not paſſe, as that holy man <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes, in the 38 chap. of that booke;<note place="margin">Iob. 38.11.</note> where he ſaith; <hi>Hitherto hath he ſaid ſhalt thou come but no further, and here ſhall thy proud
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2983:26"/>
waues be ſtayed:</hi> which barre is ſet for the ſafety of man, for elſe naturally the height of the water is higher then the higheſt hill, as may plainely appeare in the ſeuenth of <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.20.</note> when the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the great deepe were broken vp, then 15 cubites vpwards did the waters preuaile, and the Mountaines were couered, ſo that the naturall place of the water, is fifteene cubites at the leaſt higher the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth: &amp; the heathen Phyloſopher, by the twylight of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, hee could ſee ſo much, that <hi>Vicit</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it was Gods goodneſſe onely that cauſed the water to reſtraine it ſelfe, or elſe not on iot of the earth ſhould be ſeene aboue.</p>
            <p>The earth it is the heauieſt element, and therefore muſt needes ſinke downe the loweſt, and thoſe that be lighter muſt floate aloft naturally, but God for the good of man, hath altered the courſe of nature, and of the water and the earth hath made one globe, and hath cauſed that globe by man to bee compaſſed about; and ſo much of the manner of their iourney, they ſayled,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2983:26"/>
               <hi>But as they ſayled.</hi> I come vnto the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, the firſt whereof is, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours ſleepe, <hi>He fell aſleepe:</hi> The ſecurity of the iuſt and righteous is very much: The righteous, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> is bold as a Lyon, and what euer befall his body heere, yet his ſoule is like vnto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, aboue the Moone, that is alwaies cleere and quiet: ſo that as <hi>Liuie</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Scipio,</hi> we may ſafely ſay of him, <hi>Is eſt cuius animum, nec proſpera fortuna; flatu ſuo efferret, nec aduerſa infringet;</hi> He is the man whom neither proſperity can puffe vp, nor yet aduerſity can any whit deiect: An example hereof, wee haue in our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> heere, who both vpon the Land, and vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is <hi>Semper idem,</hi> one and the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame party ſtill; vpon the Land he feares not the threates of the enuious Scribes and Phariſes, vpon the Seas hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnes the rage and fury of the violent tempeſt, no ſooner is he in the ſhip, but preſently hee betakes himſelfe vnto his reſt, he fals a ſleepe, <hi>But as they ſayled he fell aſleepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then this place, giues leaue to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2983:27"/>
moue a queſtion of import; Was it I pray you (may ſome men ſay) with our Sauiour here in this place, as it was with <hi>Ionas</hi> in his tempeſt there,<note place="margin">Iona. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ion.</hi> 1. no ſooner afloate, but preſently in his Cabbin, and ſcarce in his Cabbin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was faſt? How comes this to paſſe? and how ſhall wee be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the Pſalmiſt and our Euangeliſt together? the Euangeliſt heere ſaith, <hi>But as they ſayled he fell aſleep;</hi> the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt againe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 121.4.</note> in the 121 Pſalme, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame party to, ſayes: <hi>Non dormitabat, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dormiet;</hi> He that keepeth Iſrael, ſaith he, ſhall neither ſlumber nor ſleepe: How may thoſe two agree in one, or what is the matter that now hee is ſaid to be ſo heauy as to fall aſleepe? does hee ſleepe in the Euangeliſt, and watch for euer in the Pſalmiſt ouer his?</p>
            <p>Indeed if a man do well obſerue the courſe of the world, the felicity and happineſſe of the vngodly, the miſeries and afflictions that the righteous are put vnto, hee may happily thinke, that our Sauiour does not onely ſlumber, as in this place, but indeed does nothing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2983:27"/>
elſe but ſleepe out right, nay he doth <hi>altum dormire,</hi> nothing elſe but mind his reſt; to ſee weary <hi>Sampſon</hi> grinding all day in the Mill, while the Philiſtimes are mocking him in their drunken ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.25</note> 
               <hi>Iud.</hi> 16. To ſee the weakned Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, mourning by the waters of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, whilſt their faithleſſe enemies, are bitterly ſcoffing and inſulting ouer their miſeries: <hi>Sing vs now one of your merry ſongs of Syon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 137.3.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> 137. To ſee the pampered Glutton, faring deliciouſly euery day, and the righteous <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſtarued with hunger at his very gate, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. This would make a man thinke our Sauiour not in a deepe,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.21</note> but a dead ſleepe indeed, ſo that hee might either ſay with <hi>Dauids</hi> foole,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> in the 14. Pſalme, <hi>Non eſt Deus;</hi> that there is no God at all, to controule them in their doings; or if there be a God, yet as <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> ſayes vnto <hi>Iob,</hi> in the 22 of that book, <hi>Nubes latibulum eius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; circa car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines coeli perambulat, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtra co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderat;</hi> That he hath enough to do to looke to that which is aboue, and neuer conſider what is done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the earth, al
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2983:28"/>
things go ſo prepoſterouſly, and out of order.</p>
            <p>For our Sauiour to take a nap and away, had not bene ſo much, but to be drowned in ſo deepe a ſleepe, as with our Grandfather <hi>Adam</hi> to haue a rib taken out of his ſide, and neuer to feele it; to haue <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> the voyce of a Cryer, beheaded at the requeſt, and intreaty of a whore, and yet to be ſilent for all that to; to be in a ſtorme, and the ſhip ready to founder with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnder him, and yet ſecurely ſleeping vpon his pillow, might argue at the firſt ſight, that he was ouercome with ſleep: <hi>He fell aſleepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In many things, I ſay, we may thinke our Sauiour is a ſleepe; for as he that is a ſleepe is ſtill the ſame man, whether you commend any vertue in him, or diſcommend any vitious quality hee is tainted with all, he is no more moued with your extraordinary prayſes, then he is abaſhed at your bitter inuectiues. So God oftentimes, hee lets the wicked to ſhoote vp and proſper, to flouriſh like vnto a greene Bay tree, and inioy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2983:28"/>
the world, according vnto his owne will and pleaſure, and the righteous againe like a poore Palme tree, hee is ouerladen and preſſed downe with the inſolency of others, and yet God ſeemes to be affected neither with the one, nor the others doings, hee is faſt a ſleepe and will not bee awaked; in which regard the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> as weary of his long ſufferings, &amp; willing to be releiued in his diſtreſſe, he is faine to cry aloude, and earneſtly, as it were, to wake him out of the ſleepe that he is in, to come vnto his ſuccour.<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.23.</note> 
               <hi>For thy ſake are wee killed all the day long, we are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at ſheepe for the ſlaughter, therefore awake, why ſleepeſt thou ô Lord? Ariſe, &amp;c.</hi> An earneſt admoniſher we ſee, and one that will not be ſilent, hee doubles, and trebles his ſpeech, <hi>Awake, ſleeepe not, ariſe;</hi> that if he were faſt indeed, yet his earneſtneſſe at the laſt would cauſe him to awake: and to ſpeake truth, God for the moſt part ſeemeth for to ſleepe, that ſo he might be awaked by our earneſt intreaties; for God, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes, <hi>amet nimium vehementes,</hi> is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2983:29"/>
with our prayers, as that many times hee does deny vs our ſuites, that he might heare vs continue earneſt in our prayers. And againe, if he ſhould vpon euery motion that we make vnto him grant vs our requeſts, his benefites at the laſt would come to bee contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of vs; we know it here an ordinary practiſe among men, <hi>cito data cito vileſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt,</hi> wee accompt it ſcarce worth the taking, that is not twiſe worth the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; therefore before he grant vs, hee would haue vs bee earneſt with him in deed to awake him with our prayers, if perchance hee ſhould ſeeme to bee a ſleepe. But when we haue awaked him what then, is there any redreſſe to bee had at his hand? Why yes furely, euen the ſame party that we mentioned euen now, hee found it at his hands, he was deliuered out of his diſtreſſe: <hi>Saul</hi> the perſecutor, fals deadly vpon his owne ſword, both to the deſtruction of ſoule and body, and <hi>Dauid</hi> the diſtreſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyes the Kingdome: <hi>Daniel</hi> is made protector of the Kingdome, and his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers and enemies throwne into the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2983:29"/>
Lyons den: though he ſleepe heere for a time amongſt vs, yet one day hee will awake againe; and whereas all the time of his ſleepe he hath plaid the Lambe, &amp; bene patient in his reuenge, yet when he ſhall awake, he ſhall rouze himſelfe like a Lion for to right himſelfe of al his enemies, which if it be not in this world yet in the world to come wee know it ſhall be to their greater condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noah</hi> we know, he ſlept a while, and ſuffred the ſcoffes and abuſes of his wicked ſonne <hi>Cham,</hi> but when he awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, what then? then <hi>Maledictus Canaan,</hi> then he pronounces a fearefull curſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for his lewdneſſe:<note place="margin">Gen. 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed bee Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, ſeruant of ſeruants ſhal he be:</hi> ſo, I ſay, if not in this world, yet at the end of the world, our Sauiour he ſhall curſe his enemies with a terrible curſe, a curſe of curſes: <hi>Ite mal dicti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.41</note> 
               <hi>Go yee curſed of my Father, into euerlaſting fire,</hi> a terrible and a fearefull curſe, from which God keepe vs all. But yet ſo he ſlept not here, in this place, his ſleepe now it was a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary naturall ſleepe: <hi>But as they ſayled hee fell a ſleepe.</hi> The reaſon of ſleepe in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2983:30"/>
naturall men it is yeelded by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Phyloſophers, and chiefly by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of nature; there are two cauſes, ſaith hee, of ſleepe in man, <hi>Fumus aſcendens in cerebellum,</hi> the aſcending of the fumes and vapours vp out of our ſtomacke into our head, and ſo ſurprizing of the braine, or elſe <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralis, naturae fatigatio,</hi> the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearying of our body with labour and trauell, both which were truely in our Sauiour, and yet neither the cauſe of this ſleepe of his, he had them both truely in him, becauſe in deed hee was truely man; but heere in this place, as the Diuines teach, he ſlept voluntary, as being Lord and Commander of his Humane Nature: As hee is then the <hi>Keeper of Iſrael,</hi> the Creator, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of man-kind, he cannot ſleepe, but as hee is a Man, and himſelfe made a creature, ſleepe was requiſite, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him.</p>
            <p>But yet here, I ſay, hee ſlept volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, he ſlept becauſe hee would ſleepe, hee was Lord of his Nature, and might commande it, which is not in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2983:30"/>
vs; for many of vs, oftentimes would ſleepe, but cannot, and ſometimes againe, when wee would willingly watch, our eies are moſt heauy and ouercharged with ſleepe: <hi>Illam noctem, rex duxit in ſomnem,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>Eſter.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">Eſter 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>That night the King would faine haue ſlept, but could not;</hi> And againe, the Diſciples in the 26 of <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.43</note> they could not refraine from ſleeping, when they would haue watched; <hi>and hee came and found them aſleepe againe, for their eyes were heauy;</hi> But in Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, there was no ſuch naturall imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; in the Wilderneſſe, as long as hee faſted, ſo long it may bee credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bily thought, that hee watched alſo, both which wee know, to bee aboue the courſe of ordinary nature, and in the ſixt of <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 6.12.</note> hee continued a whole night in prayer vnto his Father, and yet wee do not reade, that hee was ouercharged with heauineſſe in the morning; hee could ſleepe when he liſt, and hee could watch as long as hee liſt, and yet no impediment vnto his body, but heere hee ſleepes volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2983:31"/>
that ſo he might giue way vnto a miracle: <hi>But as they ſayled hee fell a ſleepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 4.38</note>Saint <hi>Marke</hi> recording of this ſame Story, tels vs that he did ſleepe, <hi>In puppi, ſuper ceruicale,</hi> Hee was, ſaith he, in the hinder part of the Ship, a ſleepe vpon a pillow: after his paines taking of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell vpon the Land, hee takes his reaſonable reſt in the ſhip vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the water; hee reſted his head vpon a pillow, not ſtretcht himſelfe out at length vpon the Epicures bed of eaſe, but onely laid himſelfe downe, that ſo he might bee vp againe vpon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; hee was like in this buſineſſe vnto himſelfe, poore and wanting, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo much as a boulſter of his owne to lay vnder his head, but is faine to borrow the Marriners pillow, ſo are his birth, his life, and death, the one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable vnto the other, and ſo much for this firſt Accident heere in the iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, <hi>Hee fell a ſleepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond followes, <hi>And there came downe a ſtorme of winde on the Lake.</hi> What? a ſtorme of wind come
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2983:31"/>
downe on the Lake, and Chriſt our Sauiour in the midſt of it? <hi>Creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dumne eſt, ea, ventos fuiſſe audacia?</hi> and is it poſſible, that the winde ſhould be ſo audicious as to diſturbe, either the Sea, or the Ship, in which the Lord, both of heauen and earth, was carried in? that they ſhould come violently ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, and aske no leaue of their Lord and Maiſter.</p>
            <p>Oh no, but rather as it was in the tempeſt that <hi>Ionas</hi> was toſſed in:<note place="margin">Iona 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith the Text there) <hi>ſent out a great winde into the Sea, and there was a mighty tempeſt in the Sea, ſo that the Ship was like to be broken:</hi> So in this tempeſt here, though perhaps it was not ſent of the Lord, yet by the permiſſion of the Lord wee knowe it came, that ſo hee might ſhewe his power and authority vnto his Diſciples: <hi>There came downe a ſtorme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt we obſerue an alteration, &amp; ſurely it is worthy our obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to, to mark that where our Sauiour comes, what alterations hee alwayes makes a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt men; no ſooner is he come into
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2983:32"/>
the world, but <hi>Herod,</hi> and his bloudy Councell, lay traines to intrap his life, and caſt about with themſelues, for the compaſſing of their diueliſh plot,<note place="margin">Math. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 2. a ſuddaine and vnexpected alteration amongſt the Courtiers: No ſooner is he entred into <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but the whole City is ſtraight in an vprore about him, ſaying,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.10.</note> 
               <hi>Who is this?</hi> as ſuddaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected an alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens; no ſooner is he come into the heart of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 8.2.</note> but preſently ſhe is quit of ſeuen deuils at once, as ſtrange an alteration as any of the former: No ſooner is he come into <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9.4.</note> who brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed out threatnings &amp; ſlaughters againſt the Diſciples, but of a viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſecutor, hee is become as vehement a Preacher, the greateſt alteration amongſt the reſt; no ſooner here vpon the Sea, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was calme and quiet, but ſuddainly a ſtorme and guſt of wind; <hi>And there came down a ſtorme of wind vpon the Lake, &amp;c.</hi> A ſtorme of wind vpon the Sea, and in the preſence of the Lord to? Why, how euery place is ſubiect vnto danger, there is no ſecurity any where left for
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2983:32"/>
man, no not the preſence and company of the Almighty: <hi>Nuſquam eſt ſecuritas, neque in coelo, neque in Paradiſo, multo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in hoc mundo,</hi> There is no place left for ſecurity (ſaith S. <hi>Ber.</hi>) neither heauen aboue, nor bliſſeful Paradice, much leſſe this troubleſome and tempeſtuous Sea of this preſent world wherein we liue: <hi>Lucifer</hi> one of the greateſt Angels fell in heauen, in the preſence of the Diuinity; <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradice, a place of pleaſure; <hi>Iudas</hi> in the world in the ſchoole of our Sauiour; let no man then preſume, for that is a rock that will daſh vs into pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; neither yet againe let any man deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, for that is a whirle-pit, that will ſwallow vs vp quicke, both are high waies to eternal perdition both of body and of ſoule. We muſt not deſpaire, for therfore God tooke vpon him our own nature; we muſt not preſume, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that Man <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> become God to puniſh our offences: wee muſt not deſpaire, <hi>For as I liue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 18.32. Rom 6.23. 1. Tim. 1.15</note> 
               <hi>I will not the death of a ſinner:</hi> we muſt not preſume, <hi>for the wages of ſinne is death,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul;</hi> we muſt not deſpaire, <hi>for Chriſt came into
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2983:33"/>
the world is ſaue ſinners:</hi> We muſt not preſume, for he <hi>came not to cal the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous but ſinners to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce;</hi> we muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire,<note place="margin">Eze. 18.21</note> 
               <hi>for at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſinnes from the bottome of his hart, I wil blot out his iniquity out of my remembrance, ſaith the Lord:</hi> Wee muſt not preſume, for what art thou ô man, that boaſts thy ſelfe againſt thy Maker? <hi>And what haſt thou that thou haſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.7.</note> we muſt not deſpaire, for <hi>where ſin aboundeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.20</note> 
               <hi>there grace aboundeth much more:</hi> We muſt not preſume, for ſhall we ſin that grace may abound? God forbid: but as neere as wee can, keepe an euen path, betweene deſpaire of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.12</note> &amp; the pride of our own merits; <hi>For hee that exalteth himſelfe ſhall bee brought low, and he that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exalted.</hi> Let vs ſtriue then with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to make our calling &amp; election ſure, for he that doth theſe things ſhall neuer fall, but let vs ſtil withall, worke as the ſame Apoſtle doth aduiſe vs; <hi>Cum timore &amp; tremore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.15</note> with feare and trembling; and as often as deſperation ſhall offer for to feare any of vs, let vs in the feare
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2983:33"/>
of God, with holy <hi>Bernard, Recolligera ſummum Dei miſericordiam,</hi> call into our remembrances, and apprehend it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the infinite mercies of Almighty God, ſuch as hee hath in ſtore, for all thoſe that call vpon his name; and when preſumption againe ſhall bee at our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes, ready for to puffe vs vp, let vs alſo with the ſame S. <hi>Bernard, Recollige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, domini exercituum,</hi> think vpon his iuſtice, who ſpared not his higheſt Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There came downe a ſtorme of wind vpon the lake. &amp;c.</hi> The world is the lake, vpon which the Apoſtles, and all we that doe now liue, do euery houre float; afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; troubles they are the ſtormes that are ſent downe vpon vs, to the tryall of our faith, and the perfecting of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp; at the firſt they are bitter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and we our ſelues are faint-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them: when the leaſt ſtorme of affliction doth but approach vs, then ſuddenly, with the children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, in 2. <hi>King.</hi> 4. wee cry vnto the man of God, <hi>O vir dei mors in olla,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 4.40.</note> we are vndone, for there is nothing but death &amp;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2983:34"/>
deſpaire before our eyes, but our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance againe from our troubles, that is like the Prophets meale, in the ſame place to ſweeten the pot againe, and to reſtore our ſelues vnto our ſelues.</p>
            <p>And if he be faint-hearted in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, he need not much for to wonder at it neither, for he knowes wel, both what he is, and whereof hee was made: our Sauiour in the ſecond of <hi>Canticles</hi> likens him vnto a Lilly,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> a tender flower; <hi>As the Lilly amongſt the thornes, ſo is my loue amongſt the daughters:</hi> the Lilly, ſayes S. <hi>Bernard, nec vel le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſimam, ſpinae, ſuſtinet punctionem, floris teneritudo, ſed mox vt modice premitur, perforatur,</hi> it will not endure the leaſt touch of a thorne, but ſo ſoone as it is prickt, ſo ſoone it is run through withall: ſo is it with man, the leaſt affliction is ready to make him to ſinke vnder the burden of it.</p>
            <p>And yet very neceſſary it is for him, that ſome perſecution hee ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, that ſo hee may bee knowne vnto whom he doth belong: <hi>Non dedignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in ſeruo, quod praeceſſit in domino,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Augustine:</hi> let not the ſeruant, ſayes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2983:34"/>
he, thinke ſcorne to ſuffer that which he ſees his maiſter hath ſuffered before his face: for the ſeruant is not greater then his maiſter, if the head were crowned with a crowne of thornes for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the body, why then let not the foot thinke much to catch a thorne in defence of the head againe, it is his duty for to hazard all.</p>
            <p>And neceſſary alſo it is for him, to be kept vnder in a ſecond regard: for man, as <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> ſpeakes, is like vnto a vine: now a vine, as he there ſpeakes, and we all know, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, vnleſſe it bee pruned, it will ſtraight way grow wilde; ſo man, if he haue not ſome affliction layd vpon him, to keepe him vnder, he will forget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and be ready to ſpurne againſt his maker, which makes S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to cry out, <hi>Hic vre domine, hic ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> puniſh me here O Lord in this life, and ſo in the life to come I ſhall be ſure thou wilt forgiue me.</p>
            <p>Be it then a loſſe of our goods which we ſuffer here, why ſayes Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Deus nos diſpenſatores, reliquit, non hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des:</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2983:35"/>
God, ſayes he, he makes vs his ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards here, not his heires, hee may call for an account particularly of euery one of vs, whenſoeuer it pleaſeth him, either now at this inſtant, or elſe at any other time when it ſhall ſeeme better vnto his maieſty; and God grant that we may all be ready to giue vp a iuſt and a true account vnto him.</p>
            <p>This ſame dropſie and thirſt after ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which the world hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is not naturall, but a corruption of our nature, <hi>Neſcit natura diuites, quae omnes, ex aequo pauperes generat,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayes he, doth acknowledge no rich man, who of equal condition hath made all poore: for naturally, one is prouided of no more, then is another, but all of vs as we came into the world, ſo we ſhal go againe, and how we came and muſt goe, holy <hi>Iob</hi> doth declare, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Naked came we out of our mothers wombe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>and naked muſt we return againe, the Lord giueth, and the Lord taketh away, and bleſſed for all bee the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man, for a time, may haue the vſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2983:35"/>
of Gods good creatures heere, ſome more, ſome leſſe, as it pleaſeth him; but none, not the leaſt of them, ſhall he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to carry away with him, when hee ſhal depart this preſent life. It is re-por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of the mighty <hi>Saradine,</hi> the Prince and gouernor of eleuen Nations, that when he felt death begin to approach, he commanded his winding ſheete to be ſpread in his Campe, with this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, <hi>Heere is all, of all the riches, that great Saradine ſhall carry away with him:</hi> And yet, if he had caſt his cards right, he ſhould haue found he ſhould not haue had that: for that ſhould carry him away, not hee that, and therefore in vaine was that Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But yet in this affliction of goods, it is not the vſuall wont of Almighty God, when he calles men to account, to bereaue them of all that they haue, and leaue them iuſt nothing, and ſo depart from them: hee will leaue them his grace at the leaſt, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe &amp; quiet their ſoules within them; but yet he will reſtore them temporall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2983:36"/>
goods to, when he ſhall ſee good, as we may read in the ſtory of <hi>Iob,</hi> hee tooke much from that holy man, hundreds of Oxen,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.3.</note> thouſands of Camels, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. but yet hee tooke not ſo much from him though, but that he returned him twice as much againe,<note place="margin">Iob. 42.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iob.</hi> 42. Whereupon ſayth Saint <hi>Origen, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide quid eſt amittere aliquid pro Deo, hoc eſt, multiplicata reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere tibi.</hi> See, ſaies hee, what it is to looſe any thing for the Lords ſake: it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it augmented, and multiplyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into our boſomes: and we know all, what our Sauiours promiſe in this kinde is, in the tenth of <hi>Marke, There is none,</hi> ſayes hee, <hi>that hath left houſe, or brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 10.30.</note> 
               <hi>or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife or children, or lands, for my name ſake, and the Goſpels, but he ſhall receiue an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold now in this time, houſes, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſiſters, and mothers, and children, and lands:</hi> I but how ſhall he receiue all this, the next words following ſhall make all plaine, <hi>cum perſecutione,</hi> with perſecution and trouble he ſhall receiue them all, to teach him not to ſet his minde too much vpon them, but to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2983:36"/>
his reward indeed in a better life, the iife come.</p>
            <p>Be it againe a ſickneſſe of the body, or a griefe &amp; ſorrow of the mind, which we do ſuſtaine, <hi>Certamen eſt non faenitia,</hi> ſayes <hi>Seneca</hi> the Phyloſopher, it is but a tryall of our patience, no outragious ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; and the more we ſhall be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this kinde, the more able we ſhall be to endure the miſery of it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it is an argument of his loue, and kindneſſe vnto vs, ſo the Apoſtle telles vs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Whom the Lord loueth he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ſcourgeth euery ſonne that hee receiueth:</hi> wee are not without fault, we know, that we ſhould deſerue no correction, and he againe when hee ſtriketh vs, he doth it not out of any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred vnto vs: for as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeakes, hee doth it for no other end &amp; purpoſe, but onely to amend vs, and what is his intent in amending vs, but eternally to ſaue vs? &amp; then what great hurt is there in whatſoeuer he doth vnto vs?</p>
            <p>Should hee intend our deſtruction, why he might, if it pleaſed him, once for all, take revenge vpon vs for all our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2983:37"/>
with the breath of his noſtrilles he might conſume vs quite (for what are we but Crickets and Graſſe-hoppers in compariſon of him?) and ſo might quickly confound all the ſtrength wee haue: but God hee delighteth more in mercy, to bee pittifull, then in iuſtice to take revenge vpon mankinde, <hi>Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia, ſupra omnia opera mannum ipſius,</hi> his mercy is ouer all his workes, and God in his fury does not forget his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but in it remembers to be pittifull, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto his enemies.</p>
            <p>He meant to plague the Egyptians, when hee ſhewed his power ſo ſtrange amongſt them, yet the very choyce of his weapons did ſhew his loue &amp; kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto them, he might haue brought vpon them, an Army of Beares, Wolues, Tygers, or Lyons, Beaſts that know no mercy, but liue altogether vpon the ſpoyle; but hee refuſed them all, and a more milde reuenge he would make to ſerue his turne, a poore Caterpiller, and a weake Graſſe-hopper, ſhall bee the ſcourge of his mighty power.</p>
            <p>And if hee then deale ſo kindly with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2983:37"/>
his enemies, yea, euen with thoſe, where yet he purpoſes to get himſelfe a name, as hee himſelfe profeſſes vnto <hi>Moſes: Exod.</hi> 14. then ſurely,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.4</note> hee will be much more kinde and mercifull vnto his owne children, ſuch as he profeſſes himſelfe to haue a care ouer. A milde rod indeed ſhall ſerue his turne amongſt them, the rod of the roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 17.10.</note> which flowred amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the other rods: that ſo the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the flowre might mitigate the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie and ſharpneſſe of the rod; a ling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ague, or a pining conſumption ſhall bring vs home gently vnto our father.</p>
            <p>Be it perſecution vnto death, why vnto <hi>Salomons</hi> throne, there is <hi>purpureus aſcenſus, Cant.</hi> 3. there is a purple aſcent,<note place="margin">Cant. 3.10</note> and all is ſtill vnto the beauty and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Church. The perfecteſt beauty, wee all know, it is the perfecteſt mixture of red and white; in the former part, the ſickneſſe of the body, there was whiteneſſe, as the lilley; and heere in martyrdome, there is redneſſe, as the roſe: the Church it has both her lillies, and her roſes to adorne her beautie.</p>
            <p>Martyrdome, it is termed by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2983:38"/>
Fathers, a fire, which God ſuffers to be kindled heere vpon the earth, to the tryall of man, and ſo S. <hi>Aug.</hi> cals it: where ſpeaking of Martyrdome, hee ſayes, <hi>Inventus eſt ignis, qui vnum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, alterum damnificet, ambos probet:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ſaies he, heere is a fire found out, which ſhall inrich the one, and damnifie the other, but yet proue both: the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the righteous it ſhal inrich, with eternall happineſſe, but the wicked and the reprobate, it ſhall conſume to duſt and aſhes; it ſhall try both throughly, what mettall they be made of. But in the tryall, this ſhall be the comfort of the godly man, that he ſhall not be left deſolate in this furious flame: <hi>viſitat deus &amp; in carcere ſuos, &amp; ibi plus eſt auxilij, vbi ſemper plui eſt periculi,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Amb.</hi> God he will not forſake, but come to viſit his, when they lie in the dungeon, as he did his ſeruant <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and ſtill, where there is moſt daunger, there ſtill hee will bee ſure to affoord moſt ayde and comfort: and the reaſon of it we neede not much wonder at,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.43</note> when as in the 25. of <hi>Math.</hi> he does profeſſe it himſelfe, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2983:38"/>
it is, that is ſo handled in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: <hi>in carcere eram &amp; viſitaſtis me,</hi> I was in priſon, ſaies he, and ye came vnto me: if then he wil be with them in their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in priſon, then ſurely at the ſtake he will not be abſent, but there hee will aſſiſt with all meanes needefull: I, there hee has beene knowne to haue beene preſent indeede, with many of our land, and many yet at this day are left aliue, which can teſtifie, the ſweetneſſe that the <hi>Martyrs</hi> felt, in the mideſt of theſe flames, how ioyfully they imbraced that death of theirs.</p>
            <p>And no maruaile neither, though they died with vndaunted courage, when the ſence of pain was taken quite from them, <hi>Nil crus ſentit in neruo, cum manus eſt in coelo,</hi> ſayes <hi>Tertull.</hi> the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, ſaith he, of the hand can feele but little paine, I trowe, in the flame, when the whole hand, before, is in the boſome of the Lord: then ſo many woundes, they are but ſo many open mouthes, to caroll out the praiſes of a mercifull God: and ſo much for this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Accident, <hi>there came downe a ſtorme
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2983:39"/>
of winde vpon the lake, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. and laſt <hi>Accident</hi> followes, <hi>and they were filled with water and were in ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy.</hi> Hitherto we haue heard, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeakes himſelfe, in the 13. of <hi>Mar.</hi> a rumor of warre,<note place="margin">Mar. 13.7.</note> but thankes be to God, wee haue felt no warre: wee haue heard a noiſe of the winde, but now wee are come to the trouble of the water. The Apoſtles heere, they were not, as ſometimes their forefathers were,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> in the 14. of <hi>Exod.</hi> in the <hi>red ſea,</hi> but now they are come <hi>in marimortuo,</hi> they are ouerwhelmed in the <hi>dead ſea:</hi> their liues are called in queſtion. They were filled with water, ſaies the text, and they were in ieopardie.</p>
            <p>To be in a ſtorme, and guſt of winde, there is no great matter of moment in that: many a poore ſoule amongſt vs, has indured many of them, and done well after them all too; and many dayly, wee heare, doe indure their rigour: but when their ſhip is foundred with water vnder them, when life and ſoule are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſhake hands, and depart this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, then it is high time, to cry
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2983:39"/>
out for helpe vnto the Lord: <hi>Serua nos domine, perimus:</hi> help maſter or elſe wee all periſh. They were heere in a great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, <hi>they were filled with water and they were in ieopardy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> in the 12. of the <hi>Acts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 12.4.</note> he heard a loud ſtorme, and a terrible blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering winde, when in priſon hee was clapt vp by <hi>Herod,</hi> at the requeſt of the Iewes, &amp; his life was threatned too: but Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> in the 7. of the <hi>Acts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7 58.</note> hee was in the ſhowre, when ſuch a ſhowre of ſtones were rained vpon him, that euen in the firſt moment he gaue vp the ghoſt. The noyſe then heere of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is the tumult of the people: for (beloued) there is a great affinitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe two, the <hi>water,</hi> and the <hi>people:</hi> and to ſhew how neere the one comes vnto the other, the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 65.7.</note> in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. in one <hi>verſe</hi> there, he ioynes them both together, <hi>which ſtilleſt,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>the raging of the ſea, and the noiſe of his waues, and the madneſſe of the people.</hi> Their tumult, it is ſo great, as that hee can liken them, to nothing elſe but to the ſea, in his rage, which beares downe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2983:40"/>
all that does withſtand it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14.5.</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> they were in a tempeſt, in the 14. of the <hi>Actes,</hi> when they were ſo deſpightfully vſed by the Iewes at <hi>Iconium,</hi> as that they looked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery minute to haue their liues taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them: but Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> he was wet with the ſhowre, when his head was taken off by <hi>Herod,</hi> and his body wallowed in his owne bloody gore, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Acts 12.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Deuill he is the author of theſe guſtes and ſtormes, for he ſends them downe from his ayrie manſion, where he rules and domineeres,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2 2</note> 
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. and by his boiſtrous blaſts ſtill ſeekes to croſſe the proceedings of the Lord: wee may euen ſee it in <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Sauiour, how he ſeekes to thwart and hinder his courſes. Has God, ſayes he, anoynted him with the oyle of gladnes aboue his fellowes? I will ſee if I can anoint him again with the oyle of ſadneſſe aboue his fellowes; has hee beene baptiſed with water and the holy Ghoſt? I will prouide for him another baptiſme, namely of fire; has God ſent downe the holy ghoſt, in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2983:40"/>
of a <hi>Doue,</hi> and cauſed it to light vpon his head? then I will cauſe tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and a crown of thorns, to crown his temples as wel as it; has there a voice come from heauen, ſaying, this is my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonne in whom I am wel pleaſed? then I likewiſe will prouide a voice for him, from the foote of the ladder, which ſhall ſay, if thou be the ſonne of God, come downe from the croſſe, and ſaue thy ſelfe. Thus ſtill he is contrary vnto God, in his courſes, &amp; raiſes his ſtormes to the hinderance of the Goſpell: and if he haue done thus in <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, then what may wee expect, which be his members? ſurely the vtmoſt of perils that his wit can inuent.</p>
            <p>Yet this may be our comfort, in our troubles, that howſoeuer our afflictions be, yet the Deuill has not the rod, in his owne hands: but the holy ghoſt, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and direct them ſtill, as may beſt ſerue both for his glory, and our good. And as for the Deuill, he has bound him faſt, ſo that would he neuer ſo faine, hee can ſtirre but to the length of the chaine he is linked in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:2983:41"/>Yet if our danger be ſuch, as that hee ſeekes to ſtop our breathes, and ſinke vs right downe with the multitude of his waues, then let this teach vs this leſſon with the Apoſtles here in this place, to ſtick cloſe vnto our Sauiour, &amp; not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, the rock of our defence: &amp; then we ſhall not neede to feare, though the windes blow, &amp; the ſeas beate, and the waues rage, yet we ſhal be ſecure, and at the laſt arriue where we all hope for to come one day at our wiſhed-for haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heauen; which God grant. And ſo much for this 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> accident, and this 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> verſe.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> verſe follows, in which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the miracle in the iourney, his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the wind, and appeaſing of the waters, the which of it ſelfe, without any other help, wil win our attentions to the hearing of it: for no man is ſo ſerious, but that he will be at leaſure for the acting of a miracle, how euer buſied in other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. In which there are 2 points to be conſidered of vs; the feare of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the power and authority of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: the feare of the Apoſtles, <hi>then they came to him, and awaked him, ſaying, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2983:41"/>
maiſter, we periſh:</hi> Of that firſt.</p>
            <p>Man, he is not a meere block, or ſtone, without ſence or apprehenſion, ſo that hee cannot be moued, either with his paſſion, or with his affection, (for that conceit of the Stoickes was hiſſed out of the ſchools many a day ſince) he hath them both truely and naturally within himſelfe: he hath, I ſay, both his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and his paſſions, ingrafted into his nature, and euery one of them, they haue their ſeuerall voyces, <hi>per quas etiam cum nolunt, ſe produnt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ber.</hi> through which either willingly, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times againſt their wils, they betray themſelues to the ſtanders by. Ioy, it hath a cheerefull voyce; griefe, it hath a doleful voyce; &amp; feare, it hath a timerous voyce; which paſſion of feare is none of the leaſt, but does poſſeſſe man as much as any other, &amp; makes him to vtter ſuch an vncoth noiſe, as is heard here amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Diſciples, <hi>Maiſter, Maiſter, we periſh.</hi> The inward feare wherewith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were poſſeſſed in this place, was that which made them make this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cry vnto our Sauiour for helpe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2983:42"/>
and protection in their greateſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <p>They came vnto him <hi>quia timuerunt,</hi> ſaies Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> becauſe they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; and great reaſon had they, (if we ſhall conſider it well) to feare indeede: a loude ſtorme of winde, whiſtling ouer their heads aboue, a raging and growne ſea beneath vnder feete, nothing but death before their eies: and death will make the ſtouteſt courage for to quaile.</p>
            <p>Death, ſaies <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt terrible of all things, that ſeeme terrible vnto vs: it will make vs ſet our throates vpon the taynter-hookes, and lift vp our voices like trumpets, and therefore, well ſaid the Diuell in the ſecond of <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>pellempro pelle,</hi> skin, for skin, ſaies he, and all that euer a man has will he giue for his life, ſo that he may enioy that, if it be but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for a moment longer; and therefore they had great reaſon to be affraide, when both the elements, the ayre and water, the winde and ſeas, had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:2983:42"/>They had reaſon to feare, as all men haue: they knew what they were, or if they were to learne, Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> could inſtruct them that they are <hi>fragili corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, mente ſterili,</hi> of a weake and fraile bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, of a barren &amp; fooliſh vnderſtanding: &amp; both theſe the Scriptures teach them, for the firſt <hi>homo vanitati ſimilis factus eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.4</note> ſaies the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 144. man is like a thing of nought, there is for the peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and barrenneſſe of his ſoule; and for the ſecond, <hi>inhabitat domos luteas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 4.19.</note> ſaies that holy man <hi>Iob.</hi> in the fourth of that booke, he dwels in a houſe of clay, there is for the weakeneſſe, and frailetie of his body alſo: ſo that he may iuſtly feare, in regard of either.</p>
            <p>And yet beſides both theſe, there is a worſe matter too, hee is not of himſelfe; for he is, as Saint <hi>Amb.</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>ciuitas ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſa,</hi> a beſieged City; beſieged, and that by diuers enemies; beſieged by himſelfe; beſieged by the world; beſieged by the Diuell, the common aduerſary vnto mankinde. Beſieged by himſelfe, hee is not at peace within himſelfe, but his owne fleſh it is a continuall aduerſary
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2983:43"/>
againſt him, <hi>Geſtamus laqueum noſtrum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, inimicum, carnem,</hi> we carry about vs, ſaith he, our owne fleſh, a ſworne enemy vnto vs all, borne of ſin, nouriſhed in iniquity, corrupted in our firſt beginning, but much more depraued by our wicked and vngodly cuſtome of ſinning here. A great perill, and a dangerous combatto fight againſt a home-bred enemy, eſpecially if we ſhall conſider, that we our ſelues, we are but ſtrangers here, and that It is in his natiue Country, and therefore hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aduantages which we cannot get.</p>
            <p>And that which is worſt of all, this dangerous enemy we muſt not deſtroy neither, ſo S. <hi>Amb,</hi> tels vs, <hi>Hunc inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ſuſtentare cogimur, non perimere:</hi> we are, ſaith he, bound to maintaine, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for to kill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> our ſoules &amp; bodies they are married together by God himſelfe, and thoſe that God hath ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let no man be ſo bold as once to dare to ſeparate aſunder; <hi>Cogimur dilige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vt ſponſus ſponſam, Adam Euam,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ber.</hi> we muſt be ſo far from hating of our fleſh, as that we are commanded for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2983:43"/>
to cheriſh it and loue it entirely, to loue it as the husband ought to loue his wife, <hi>Adam</hi> his <hi>Eue. Hinc illae lachrymae,</hi> hence growes that fearefull danger, a life of danger, a world of danger, it is like the remnant of the <hi>Iebuſites,</hi> in the Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. we may employ it in labour but we muſt not ſlay it,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.</note> and the more we ſhall employ it, the leſſe dangerous or hurtfull it will proue vnto vs: but yet it is fearefull though, to haue ſo treacherous a companion about vs, an enemy that ſhall continually ſleepe in our boſomes. The company of ſuch an one, for the moſt part, is conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious.</p>
            <p>He is beſieged againe by the world, a ſubtle enemy, and one that makes a ſhew of a faithfull friend, ſuch an one as cunning <hi>Iael</hi> was vnto fearefull <hi>Siſera,</hi> in the fourth of <hi>Iudges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 4.18.</note> who perceiuing of him flying, cries from her Tent dore, turne in my Lord, turne in to mee and feare not: and when ſhe hath him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhe begins to make much of him, ſhe giues him milke to lull him aſleepe, and ſhe couers him that he take no cold,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2983:44"/>
but no ſooner is hee faſt, but that ſhee puts her hand vnto the nayle, and her right hand to the work-mans hammer, ſo the world it beginnes with milke, but it endes with a hammer, they all ſhall finde it that liſt to proue it.</p>
            <p>The beſt way that I know to be rid of this enemy, is not to haue at all to doe with it, to ſequeſter our ſelues, as much as wee can, from the affaires of this world, and to place our hearts there, where one day wee may ſafely inioy them againe: let our ſoules like Eagles mount aloft, flie aboue the Cloudes, and ſeate themſelues in the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and there we are ſure they ſhall be moſt ſafe. To meddle with this worldly mucke, it is but to inſnare our ſelues with fooliſh vanities: The bird that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtoupes in her flight, at one time or other ſhe is intrapped, before ſhee bee aware of it; either ſhe is caught with a lime-twig, by the wing at vnawares, or elſe ſhe is faſt by the feete in the net, or one way or other, ſhee is betrayed to her ouerthrow; ſo the ſoule that lookes downeward vpon euery baite, at the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2983:44"/>
length it is inſnared, before it is aware, and ſubiected vnto the vanities of this world. The beſt way therefore to rid vs of it, is not to haue to do with it, but keepe our ſelues aloft, whither it cannot aſcend: <hi>Surſum cor, qui ſurſum habes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> As our eies were frame at the firſt to looke vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſo let our heartes learne to ſeate themſelues there, and then we ſhall be ſure to be quite of this enemy.</p>
            <p>Hee is a third way beſieged by the deuill, a ſworne enemy vnto all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and hee is the moſt dangerous of all other enemies. For where as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enemies haue but one onely way to intrap vs in, <hi>viz.</hi> craft and ſubtlety, this aduerſary hee hath many, he is both <hi>Callidus</hi> and <hi>Potens,</hi> both a ſubtle and a ſlie inſinuator of himſelfe in into vs, and withall hee is a mighty and a potent aduerſary againſt vs.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, his craft and ſubtlety, it is <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> his note of him, that he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an admirable Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, deepe and pollitique in his deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and euery courſe that he ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2983:45"/>
vs to, it ſhall ſeeme like vnto <hi>Achitophels</hi> counſell,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.23.</note> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. as if a man had enquited at the Oracle of God: and to further his deuiſes that they may not ſeeme to be without ſucceſſe, he will, as in ancient time vnto King <hi>Saul,</hi> appeare vnto vs vnder <hi>Samuels</hi> Mantell,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 28.14.</note> that we ſhall not thinke it to be he, but rather God himſelfe that ſpeakes vnto vs.</p>
            <p>But we muſt learne to beware of his cloſe treacheries: and that we may be the more ſure of him, and not lull our ſelues aſleepe in careleſſe ſecurity, but be as vigilant to preuent, as he is dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to ouerthrow: <hi>Naz.</hi> tels vs in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, that we muſt be ſure to keep a priuy watch about vs continually, for that he is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a night-thiefe, as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a noone-day deuill, and will come craftily ſtealing on vpon vs, before we be aware of him; nay, when as we are moſt ſecure, then is he moſt buſily caſting about, and plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt vs: ſo that day and night, both in our labour, and in our quiet, wee muſt be ſure to haue a vigilant eye
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2983:45"/>
to him wards.</p>
            <p>And for the ſecond, his Might and Power, it is very great: wee muſt fight, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>aduerſus prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus &amp; poteſtates,</hi> againſt Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers; nay, againſt the Prince and God of this world:<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.31.</note> for ſo Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtiles him in his 12 Chapter and 31 verſe, where he ſaith, Now is the Prince of this world caſt out: hee hath whole Nations his attendants and followers, as we may ſee, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.17.</note> the <hi>Sabaeans</hi> and <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi> and to ſpeake truth, what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is there vpon the earth, wherein his power and might is not acknowledged? So that wee may ſafely ſay, that which the Iewes in the 12.<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.19.</note> of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell ſayd of our Sauiour, <hi>Ecce totus mundus,</hi> behold the world indeed doth nothing elſe but runne after him: ſo that worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he may be feared, for his puiſſant Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, beſides his owne inuincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.14</note> which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the 22 <hi>Pſalm.</hi> likens vnto a ramping and roaring Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, terrible and fearefull, for the aſſault it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>So that there muſt be great heed and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2983:46"/>
diligence vſed againſt this enemy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, hee being in the firſt, as <hi>Nazian.</hi> teacheth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a crafty Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and teacheth men what himſelfe neuer learned. And in the ſecond, ſaith S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an ouer po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull aduerſary: in both kindes feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in the one for his ſlights, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his force.</p>
            <p>And as hee is both thus ſubtile and ſtrong, ſo is hee alſo of a working tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; his nature it is proportionable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his name. <hi>Beelzebub, Muſcarum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> is his name in Scripture, the God of Flies; who, though you flap him away neuer ſo often, yet hee will flye to the ſame place againe: he will neuer leaue vs ſo long as we be here, if his ſtorme will not quell vs, yet hee will try what the raging of the water may effect vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: he is reſtleſſe in his plots, and if one temptation will not hurt vs, yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſhall be ſure to aſſaile vs;<note place="margin">Eſa. 42.3.</note> and the quenching of the ſmoaking Flaxe, and the breaking of the bruiſed Reed, is ſtill the marke that he leuels at, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42. <hi>Si auaritia proſtrata est exurgit libido,</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2983:46"/>
ſaith S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> if greedy couetouſneſſe will not ſeize vs, yet hee will try what itching luſt may effect vpon vs: is luſt repelled? yet ambition may chance to ſtrike a great ſtroake with vs: is ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion quenched? yet anger (perhaps) may put vs out of our Bias: is wrath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? yet enuy ſhall trouble vs: is enuy forgotten? yet iealouſie ſhall affright vs. And thus reſtleſſe, hee followes vs with all his inventions, ſo that no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, if the Diſciples were ſo fearefull, when ſuch traytors were within them, ſuch enemies without them, ſuch weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on all ſides, for to hold out long; ſuch ſtormes of winde aboue, ſuch ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſeas beneath, that <hi>then they came vnto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They came vnto him, euen at the laſt gaſpe, when the windes blew, and the ſeas beate, when their ſhip was ready to founder vnder them, and they as ready to take their oathes all, to bee deaths true ſeruants, then they came vnto him, ſaith my Text.</p>
            <p>The Heathen, they were ſomewhat ſtrange in their reſolutions, and when
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2983:47"/>
hope ſeemed deſperate, then ſcorned they any longer to hope for it; and it was one of their chiefe wiſhes, and a great eaſe (as rhey thought) vnto their miſeries, to bee ſwallowed vp quicke, and deuoured of death, as the Apoſtles here were like to be: from which kinde of death we do in our <hi>Lyturgie,</hi> earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray to bee deliuered; that as God would deliuer vs all from vnpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared death, ſo hee would deliuer vs likewiſe from ſudden and vnexpected death, becauſe that commonly ſudden death, and vnprepared death, they goe both together: we cannot liue ſo wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here, not the beſt of vs all, but if God ſhould take vs vpon the preſent, wee might haue many things obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, which we would bee all wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhould be concealed in that great and generall day of Iudgement. God grant vs all time of repentance here, &amp; hee grant vs alſo, that wee doe not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend that time that he giues vs, but in it heartily repent vs of our ſins, that ſo in the laſt and finall day of iudgement, we may all haue that bleſſing pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2983:47"/>
vpon vs, that the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> pronounceth vpon all the righteous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. <hi>Beatiquorum remiſſae ſunt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.</note> bleſſed is the man whoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe is forgiuen, and whoſe ſin is couered. Then bleſſed ſhall they be vnto whom the Lord will impute no ſin. And as for thoſe who, thinke they liue ſo warily, as that they are alwayes prepared for death, let them ſtand vpon their owne innocency, and haue no part in this prayer of ours.</p>
            <p>The heathen (I ſay) they thought it a happineſſe to haue a ſudden death to light vpon them: and ſo <hi>Plinie</hi> in his ſeuenth Booke, and 53. Cpapter wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, that that might bee his lot; and the Poet is not farre behinde him when he ſaith:
<q>
                  <l>Mitius ille perit, ſubita qui mergitur vnda:</l>
                  <l>Quam ſua qui liquidis brachia laſſat aquis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He dies eaſier (ſaith he) who at the firſt dop doth loſe his life, then hee that in ſwimming doth ſtruggle to drawe breath. But wee that are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. wee muſt reſolue our ſelues
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2983:48"/>
on the contrary opinion, their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance it was that cauſed them to wiſh for it: but we, we know beſides the manner of death, we know (I ſay) of a great account, which euery one of vs is to make, when this life ſhall be ended; a matter that the Heathen ſcarce euer dreamed of, where wee muſt make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, not onely for thoſe ſinnes of old age, which the Prophet in the 38 of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 38.15.</note> calles <hi>annos,</hi> ſinnes of yeares, ſinnes of great ſtanding; but as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeakes in the 25 <hi>Pſal. Delicta inventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 25 7.</note> ſins of wanton and reckleſſe youth; and not onely thoſe neither, but in the 19 <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12</note> for ſecret ſins, that is (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his <hi>Confeſſions</hi>) for the ſinnes we haue committed in our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, before we knew either good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: that we may haue the fewer indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments preferred againſt vs, in that great and generall day of iudgement: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee deſire reſpite for repentance here in this world, which God grant vs all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They came vnto him:</hi> but how? <hi>Non paſſibus, ſed precibus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:2983:48"/>
not ſo much by their earthly paces, (though we muſt conceiue, that euen in thoſe they haſted vnto him) as by their winged prayers they poaſted towards him, they praied vnto him: for had they not humbly ſupplicated, as well as run vnto him, they might all very well haue periſhed in the furious tempeſt.</p>
            <p>To pray, it is naturall for Man: and ſo much <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> by the purblinde eye of nature could ſee; <hi>Natura,</hi> ſairh he, <hi>inſeruit homini vt ſacrificet,</hi> Man by nature, ſaith hee, is made a continuall Beades-man vnto his maker, alwayes to haue recourſe vnto him; and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of nature, grace hath confirmed from time to time in the righteous man, to haue recourſe vnto his Maker: ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> in his diſtreſſe, in the 68 <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.16</note> when he is in-girt, and compaſſed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with his many enemies, he turnes himſelfe vnto the Lord, <hi>Exaudi me Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miue,</hi> heare me, O Lord, ſaith hee, for thy louing kindneſſe is good, turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, according vnto the multitude of thy tender mercies, and hide not thy face from thy ſeruant: for I am in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2983:49"/>
heare me ſpeedily, and draw nye vnto my ſoule, and redeeme it, deliuer me becauſe of mine enemies, &amp;c. So good <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> in 2.<note place="margin">2. Chron. 20.13.</note> 
               <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. he ſaith, <hi>cum ignoremus quid agere debeamus,</hi> when we know not, O Lord, ſaith he, what to doe, then our eyes they are vpon thee. And ſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> wiſhes that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſhould be, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. Caſt all your care vpon him, for hee careth for you: and if at any time they ſhould haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto God, then moſt eſpecially in their troubles and aduerſities: when mens ſoules are brought low vnto hell, then they ſhould call vpon his name heartily indeed, and then aboue other times, hee expects to bee called vpon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.15.</note> Call vpon mee, ſaith God, in the day of trouble, and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes, that it is Gods <hi>Memorandum</hi> vnto men to call vpon him, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oce te,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>vt inuoces me:</hi> behold, O man, ſaith hee, I put thee in minde of it, if thou haue forgotten, that then aboue all other times, thou haue recourſe vnto me.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2983:49"/>
Nay many times Almighty God doth lay afflictions and troubles here vpon men, that they might bethinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their Prayers, and flye vnto him in their ſore diſtreſſe. We may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the courſe of it: By aduerſitie God brings men firſt into a doubt and feare, and then by feare into an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of their owne neceſſitie and weakneſſe; and ſo conſequently into a deſpaire of ſuccour in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and by deſpairing in their owne meanes, to thinke of meanes that may bee profitable vnto them, and ſo at the laſt, to the conſideration of Gods vnſpeakeable loue and kindneſſe to them-wards.</p>
            <p>And out of this againe, conſidering that his mercie is great, and his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from euerlaſting, hee raiſeth vs vp againe to an aſſured truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his mercies, and out of this confidence, wee are bold to make our Prayers and Petitions vnto our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And therfore if either voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or anger, or pride, or any other ſin ſhall be ready to attempt vs, our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2983:50"/>
onely muſt bee to pray againſt them with <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 44 <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.23</note> 
               <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urge Domine,</hi> awake, why ſleepeſt thou, O Lord, ariſe, and caſt vs not off for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; wherefore hideſt thou thy face, and forgetteſt our affliction and our trouble? And in our prayers I make no queſtion, but we ſhall finde comfort, if not deliuerance ſpeedily. If then any periſh, it is as God himſelfe ſpeakes in the 13 of <hi>Oſe. Perditio tua ex te ô Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſe. 13.14</note> his deſtruction it is from himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath neglected his dutie vnto the Lord, in calling vpon him to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They came vnto him,</hi> and good reaſon too: for if we would any thing with the Lord, it is all the reaſon that may be, that we come vnto him, we haue need of him, not he of vs; then we muſt call, nay we muſt cry vnto the Lord:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Clamaui ad Dominum,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid.</hi> I cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the Lord with my whole voyce, and he heard me out of his holy Hill: we muſt come and pray vnto him, <hi>Then they came vnto him. &amp;c.</hi> What the Apoſtles here did in their perſons, that wee muſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2983:50"/>
do if we want any thing, in our owne; nay, whether we want any thing, or no, it is our duty for to do it; and the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the righteous, they are of no ſmall force or efficacie with God, to obtaine a bleſſing from him; euery one of them is as a forcible Engine to open Heauen gates, and to draw downe a bleſſing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of him that ſent it vp. So S. <hi>Bernard</hi> telles vs out of that place of the Goſpell. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. concerning the poore Publican. <hi>Dum non auderet oculos ad Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los eleuare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>ipſum Coelum potuit ad ſe incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare,</hi> ſaith hee: Whilſt the Publican durſt not lift vp his eyes in his prayers, vnto heauen, ſuch was the force of his prayers with God aboue, as that hee bowed the heauens, and made them deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend downe vnto his prayers. But yet by the way it were not amiſſe for to aske the queſtion, What prayers are theſe, that are of ſuch power &amp; efficacie with the Lord? it is not euery one that is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in his name,<note place="margin">Math. 7.21</note> ſo our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe telles vs, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. <hi>Non omnis qui dicit, Domine, Domine,</hi> not euery one that ſaith vnto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2983:51"/>
into the Kingdome of heauen, much leſſe euery time that he ſaith it, ſhall haue his requeſt. But before our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers we muſt prepare our ſelues to pray by ſerious meditation, <hi>Meditatio do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet quid deſit, oratio ne deſit obtinet,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard:</hi> by meditation we learne to know what is wanting vnto vs, and by prayer we obtaine that it ſhall not be wanting. That ſhewes which is the right way that we muſt walke, this tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs how to walke when we haue found the path. By meditation wee know the dangers and the perils that hang ouer our heads, and by prayer we auoyd them all, and eſcape away ſcot-free.</p>
            <p>And yet before we can come to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate aright, our heart it muſt be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med aright for it, and that muſt bee by an earneſt and hearty repentance for our ſinnes, which is <hi>Magna ſpongia,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calles it, the great Spunge that wipes them all away out of the fight of the Lord. And herein lies an eſpeciall duty of the Prieſt, if he ſhall be required thereunto, to know
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2983:51"/>
how dangerous the ſinne is that a man is tainted withall; not to flatter his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in his ſinne, but to let him know the true weight and danger of it, that ſo he may throughly repent him of his ſin, and learne to returne to God againe. For as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Imperitus eſt medicus,</hi> &amp;c. he is an vnskilfull Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith hee, and a worſe Surgeon a great deale, who ſeeing of a putrified ſore will handle it gently, and ſuffer the corruption to remaine in it ſtill; and ſo by his fooliſh pitie ouerthrowes his patient, whilſt he is afraid to apply ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his cauteries, or his ſearing medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. <hi>Aperiendum eſt vulnus &amp; ſecandum,</hi> ſaith he, the wound muſt be ſearched &amp; launced, and the bottome of it felt: let the patient in the meane time rage and rosre; yet when hee is recouered, hee will giue him thankes for his cruell loue.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that ſow pillowes vnder mens elbowes, and take away repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for their ſins, make men beleeue their ſinnes are but motes; when the weight is ſo great, that God himſelfe is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2983:52"/>
forced to groane vnder the burthen of them, <hi>Amos</hi> 2. they doe as much as in them lies, ſhut vp the gate of all true repentance: ſo that whilſt with the falſe Prophets, they cry, <hi>Pax, pax, &amp; non eſt pax,</hi> peace, peace, when there is nothing leſſe then peace to be expected: whilſt they promiſe a falſe peace vnto the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the hope of eternall peace is vtterly loſt from them.</p>
            <p>But in this caſe there are many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull, euen of the great ones amongſt vs, who know not what to anſwere to a diſtreſſed wight, that ſhall craue their aduiſe and helpe: but the fault, for the moſt part, it lies in themſelues. <hi>Nemo nos interrogat,</hi> ſo few there are that craue the aduice of their Teacher, as that the caſe of Conſcience lies quite neglected: ſome one or two (perhaps) when they lye in a cold ſweate, they ſend for a Preacher, and then hee muſt giue them a little <hi>Opiate</hi> Diuinitie, that may skinne, but not heale or helpe the fore a whit.</p>
            <p>Let vs repent our ſelues whilſt wee are luſty and ſtrong, and then wee ſhall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2983:52"/>
feeele the fruite of it when we lye ſicke and weake vpon our beddes. And for this ſame late repentance, is S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> note, <hi>Poenitentiaquae à moriente tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum petitur, timeo ne ipſa moriatur:</hi> he is afraid it will bee dead as ſoone, if not ſooner, then the partie that lies ſicke.</p>
            <p>But true repentance it is the meanes to right meditation, and right meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to hearty prayer; and without hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prayer it is but in vaine to come vnto the Lord: and yet againe it is but in vaine for vs to repent, vnleſſe withall we proceed to feruency of prayer. <hi>Caine</hi> ſorrowed for his ſinnes, when hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his ſinnes were ſo great, as God could not forgiue them. And <hi>Iudas,</hi> when he cryed out, I haue ſinned in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the innocent bloud; but yet they had neither of them grace to aske forgiueneſſe for their ſinnes; which had they done heartily, and as they ought, I am fully perſwaded they ſhould haue found pardon for their great offences.</p>
            <p>Repentance it is the <hi>Superſedeas</hi> that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2983:53"/>
diſchargeth all bonds of ſinne; and Prayer, it is the bucket by which wee draw grace from the everlaſting foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. Let vs continue drawing then, till we may aſſure our ſelues we haue a good meaſure of grace within vs, and neuer leaue him, who is able to adde more to him, that hath the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of it in him. Let vs flye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord by prayer: and ſince our many ſinnes, like ſo many fierce <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> haue not ſticked to murther the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah;</hi> let our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant teares, and humble prayers, like ſo many Bees, come and ſucke the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at the flowers of his paſſion: let them aſcend vp early in the morning, like incenſe into his noſtrils, and cloſe the afternoone againe like an euening ſacrifice: then ſhall we truly come vnto the Lord, and as we ought to do; then ſhall they awaken him, though hee bee faſt aſleepe, and obtaine a bleſſing for vs that offered them vp. <hi>Then they came vnto him and awaked him, ſaying, Maſter, Maſter,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Title of Maſter, here, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2983:53"/>
a little pauſe: you call me Lord and Maſter, ſaith our Sauiour in the thirteenth of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell;<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.13.</note> and you doe well, for ſo I am. Is not hee Maſter of them, who is Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Nature it ſelfe? vnto whom all things both in heauen aboue, and in earth beneath, doe willingly obey? He is Maſter of them, for he made them all, <hi>Dixit &amp; facta ſunt,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> he ſpake but the word, and all things were made, hee commanded and they ſtood all faſt: hee did but ſpeake the word, let the earth bring forth her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and alſo the waters, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently both earth and ſea, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with all manner of varietie. <hi>Brevis ſermo, ſed valde vehement,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> a ſhort ſpeech it was indeede, ſaith hee, that God ſpake; but yet withall it was a ſpeech, that was full of power, the efficacie of that ſpeech, it brought forth the greateſt as well as the leaſt creatures, and in the ſame time too: for in the ſame time the whole was made, that hee was making of a Frogge; <hi>Non laborat in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2983:54"/>
maximis Deus, non faſtidit in minimis,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> God (ſaith hee) did not labour in the making of the greateſt things, nor yet contemne the making of the meaneſt: hee made all things by his power, and therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily is Maſter of all.</p>
            <p>Was hee not worthy to bee Maſter of Man, as well as of other Creatures, when hee made ſuch diuers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie Elements for to meete together in one and the ſelfe ſame body, and accord in one, Fire and Water, Aire and Earth, Heate and Cold, and all in one and the ſelfe ſame place, and yet hath ſo tempered them together, as that one is the defence and maintenance of the other? Nay more then this, ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, Mirabilis ſocietas:</hi> In man hee hath made a wonderfull ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: for in him Heauen and Earth, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty and Baſeneſſe, Excellencie and Pouertie, hee hath matched together. What is higher then the ſpirit of life? What is baſer then the ſlime of the earth? his ſoule it was infuſed into him, the ſpirit of life: his body it was made
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2983:54"/>
of the duſt of the earth. This was that that made <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> to break into that ſame exclamation of himſelfe, what great and wonderfull miracle was within himſelfe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. I am litle, and yet I am great; I am humbled, and yet I am exalted; I am mortall, and yet I am immortall; I am earthly, and yet I am heauenly: little in body, but great in ſoule; humble, as being earth, but yet exalted aboue the earth; mortall, as he that muſt dye; immortall, as he that ſhall riſe againe; earthly, as whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was taken from the earth; heauenly, as whoſe ſoule was breathed feom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. And will not all this then make him well deſerue the Name and Title of Maſter amongſt vs?</p>
            <p>Yes: But here hee hath a double Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Maſter, Maſter. What of that? Why hee hath a double Maſterſhip: he was their Maſter, <hi>Iure creationis,</hi> by the right of their creation, but much more Maſter, <hi>Iure redemptionis,</hi> by right and title of their redemption: when man had loſt himſelfe, and defaced that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2983:55"/>
image that God at the firſt had left within him, then came our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus in, a mercifull Redeemer, and reconciled his Father and Man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againe. Henceforth let vs not repine at the fall of our Grand-father: for Chriſt our Sauiour hath made ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for it. Was he caſt away for the price of an Apple? Why yet he is redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for a great deale leſſe, he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed in meere loue and pitie.</p>
            <p>The ſixth day of the weeke, as it is thought, <hi>Adam</hi> fell (for it is thought that he fell the ſame day that hee was made) the ſixth day of the weeke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſteritie were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from death. The ſame day that he fell he was redeemed. And as God in the beginning reſted on the ſeuenth day, ſo Chriſt our Sauiour, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine, ſabbatizanit in monumento,</hi> kept holy the Sabboth euen in the graue, to teach vs to make more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that day, then the world vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doth in theſe our times. For, for all that belonged vnto the ſaluation of man, he finiſhed that vpon the croſſe,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2983:55"/>
before his departure hence, when hee cried, <hi>Conſummatum eſt,</hi> all is finiſhed.<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.30.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19. Then all was performed that was requiſite for vs; and hauing fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his worke, he reſted as ſecurely in his graue, as the moſt ſecure man of vs all doth reſt in his bed.</p>
            <p>And in this redemption which he ſo kindly performed for vs, there are two things eſpecially to bee conſidered of vs, <hi>Modus</hi> and <hi>Fructus,</hi> the manner and the fruit of our redemption.</p>
            <p>The Manner, it was wonderfull, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inanitio Dei,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, the emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying of God, the fulneſſe of all things. The emptying of him (I ſay) and that in three regards: Firſt, into the fleſh. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, vnto the death. Thirdly &amp; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnto the death of the croſſe. O who can worthily eſteeme theſe three as hee ought to do, his worth, his humilitie, his loue vnto mankinde? That the God of all Maieſty ſhould be cloathed with the garment of humane fleſh. That hee ſhould conſent to dye, and that hee ſhould dye ſo miſerable and curſed a death. Here ſpeech muſt faile vs, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2983:56"/>
our ſafeſt eloquence muſt bee admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſometimes in the feare of God call our ſelues to account for theſe things, and thinke what great things the Lord hath done for euery one of our ſoules: and then let vs be aſhamed at our owne vnthankfulneſſe againe, that he being Lord of all, became obedient and ſeruant for the very worſt of vs; Of being rich in all things, became poore and miſerable in moſt that were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; That of the word he became fleſh; Of the ſonne of God that he ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſonne of baſe and mortall man. Let vs remember, that though at the firſt we were made of nothing, yet that afterwards we were not redeemed of nothing. In ſixe dayes at the firſt, God made heauen and earth, and all things that in them were contained: but in the redemption of Man, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour was three and thirty yeares and vpwards, a working of it vpon the earth.</p>
            <p>O how much in that time, did he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for our ſakes? The neceſſities of the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2983:56"/>
fleſh, the contempt and ſcorne of the world, the temptations both of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and of mankinde. Can wee thinke that pouerty in all that time did not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe him? nor ſhame did not touch him? nor yet the wrath and anger of his Father any whit amaze him? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, certainly (beloued) the leaſt of all theſe did touch him neere; and the greateſt (that was the fury of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) did make him make that lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cry vpon the Croſſe, the like wherof was neuer heard in Ages before, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall be heard againe, vnto the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the world, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? Yet thus, O Lord, didſt thou worke the ſaluation of Man, and wonderfully towards him hath beene thy loue. Let vs thinke of theſe things ſeriouſly, let vs thinke of them often; and then I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but we ſhall thinke we haue great reaſon to think him a double Maſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. <hi>And they came vnto him and awaked him, ſaying, Maſter, Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet the cauſe of his double Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation here in this place, it was the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2983:57"/>
feare of the Apoſtles that infuſed it ſelfe into them, and the earneſt deſire that they had to be deliuered from their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger, was that that made them double their ſpeeches vnto him, Maſter, Maſter. What wee heartily wiſh for, we often repeate. <hi>Helpe, Helpe,</hi> we cry in time of danger, <hi>Reſcue, Reſcue,</hi> in time of diſtreſſe. So is it here with our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in this place, in this time of feare, when the ſtorme raged, and the ſeas went high. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olvuntur vt aequora montes,</hi> as the Poet ſpeakes: one billow toſſed them vp as high as heauen, and another ſuddenly drenched them in the botome of the deep. When life almoſt had quite forſaken them, and death was ready to ſeize vpon them, then they cry vnto him, Maſter, Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui neſcit orare, diſcat nauigare,</hi> ſaith the Latine Prouerbe: if there be any ſo pampred here vpon the land, as I am afraid many thouſands there are, that haue forgot their duties vnto the Lord, neuer think of him, but when they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his name to ſweare by: let them go to ſea, and if they bee not paſt grace
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2983:57"/>
quite, ſo that they haue not, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes, <hi>Cauteriatam conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> a ſeared conſcience, that can feele no touch of remorſe, hee ſhall bee taught once a day at the leaſt, to call vpon the name of the Lord. <hi>And they came vnto him, and awaked him, ſaying, Maſter, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, we periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our life, though it be in a dangerous place, as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> telles, <hi>Quam diu in ſalo iſto, tam diu inter naufragia:</hi> ſo long as we liue in the ſea of this world, ſo long alſo wee are in continuall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſhipwrack, to be ſpoyled, and we our ſelues doe continually ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our ſoules and bodies both, with ſinne, as that euery day we preſſe dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and deeper towards the bottomleſſe pit of hell. Yet ſuch is the friendſhip that is contracted betweene the body and the ſoule, by the long familiarity and acquaintance each of other, as that they are loath to part and leaue each others company: They deſire to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue longer together, if longer it might be, and they care not what ſhifts they vſe for the enioying their deſire. That
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2983:58"/>
made Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to deny his Maiſter, becauſe hee thought it would call his life in queſtion: And all the Diſciples, for feare of death, withdrew themſelues from our Sauiours company, becauſe they ſaw thoſe friends muſt part, that had liued ſo long combined together. Terrible and fearefull it is vnto man, to thinke of the diſſolution of ſoule and body, <hi>Anima abſoluitur, corpus reſoluitur,</hi> as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes; where the ſoule is freed, and ſet at libertie, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againe reſolued into the firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. This is that which the natural man cannot endure to heare of; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpon the very thought of it, hee is ready with the Apoſtles to cry out for helpe, Maſter, Maſter, wee periſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <p>But yet this was not the onely cauſe though of their crying out in this place, though that might helpe to ſet an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent vpon it: for they knew that there was a neceſſity by nature laid vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, once for to dye. <hi>Intraſti vt cocires</hi> was a condition annexed to our creation. We muſt make roome for others, as well as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2983:58"/>
others before haue done for vs. And ſo much the Heathen Poet could ſay, <hi>Omnes vna manet nox, &amp; calcanda ſemel via lethi:</hi> they muſt not thinke much to vndergoe that which all are enioyned neceſſarily vnto. Equalitie is the chiefe ground-worke of equitie; and who can complaine to be comprehended where all are contained? eſpecially when they ſhall conſider the extraordinarie bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that death ſhall bring with it, <hi>viz.</hi> the taking away of ſinning any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Death, it was once laid vpon man, as a puniſhment for ſinning, <hi>quo die come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris, &amp;c.</hi> what day ſoeuer thou ſhalt eate of the forbidden fruit, thou ſhalt certainly dye. Death there is appointed as the puniſhment to ſinne, but now it is giuen as a benefite and remedy vnto man, to keepe him from ſinning any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Morere ne pecces,</hi> dye ſoone that thou mayſt not ſinne more againſt thy maker. <hi>Quod tunc timendum fuit, vt non peccaretur, nunc ſuſcipiendum eſt, ne pecce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi> what was once feared, is now a benefite vnto mankinde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:2983:59"/>But the feare of eternall death was that that did amaze them more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the other particulars ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. To periſh both in body and in ſoule, and that eternally too; this is that that would make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awake him quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. To periſh when they were but <hi>Semi-chriſtiani,</hi> halfe Chriſtians, like <hi>Agrippa</hi> in the 26 of the <hi>Acts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 26.28</note> thou perſwadeſt me almoſt (ſaith hee to <hi>Paul</hi>) to bee a Chriſtian: to periſh when they were but newly initiated into the Schoole of Chriſt, before they knew the myſteries belonging to their ſaluation neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, was that that made them cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud. They were ignorant in the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall poynts: for the Holy Ghoſt doth teſtifie of them in diuers places, That they knew not the Scriptures, that they vnderſtood not that ſaying of his, that they knew him not yet to bee the Meſſias, and then how fearefull a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was for them to dye vnreſolued, you your ſelues by your ſelues, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily iudge. This feare here of eternall periſhing, made them cry ſo earneſtly to bee deliuered from the feare of death:
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2983:59"/>
               <hi>Maiſter, Maiſter, we periſh:</hi> in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; but which is fearefull to be thought vpon alſo, we periſh euerlaſtingly in our ſoules in hell.</p>
            <p>In our bodily conflicts here vpon the earth, either the ſence of paine is quite taken away by death; or elſe if our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bee ſtrong and luſty, it ſoone in wreſtling ouercomes the paines of death; but in this ſecond death the death of the ſoule, the griefe remaines for euermore, that ſo our nature might be afflicted without any end, and our nature indures alſo, that for euer it might bee puniſhed in the endleſſe flames, for tranſgreſſing againſt ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite a God: neither ſhall faile, neither nature nor paine, that ſo both may bee eternall vnto the wicked. The firſt death doth ſeparate the vnwilling ſoule from the body; but the ſecond death keepes the ſoule, though much vnwillingly, for euer in paine together with the body; from which paine God for his Chriſt Ieſus ſake, keepe vs all, <hi>Amen.</hi> And ſo we are come to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall concluſion of theſe ſame words.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2983:60"/>
               <hi>Then he aroſe and rebuked the wind, and the raging of the water, and they ceaſed, and there was a calme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto our Sauiour hath beene pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in theſe troubles, and reſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe quietly in theſe ſtormy guſts both of winde and water: but now he begins to bee a Maſter indeed, and takes vpon him both the bridling of the one, and of the other: he rebukes the winde, and appeaſes the raging of the troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and at his rebuke they both ceaſe, and there is a calme.</p>
            <p>But before we come to the appeaſing of this raging ſtorme, this firſt word <hi>Then</hi> will make vs ſtay a while by the way. <hi>Then he aroſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then.</hi> When was that, may ſome man ſay? Why when, but when the rage was greateſt, in the midſt of the guſt, when the windes whiſtled loud, and the ſea went high: when their ſhip was full of water, and Mariners and paſſengers were all at their wits end: <hi>Then hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe and rebuked the winde, ond the raging of the water, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A dangerous time (beloued) when
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2983:60"/>
cunning had left them, and the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe waues muſt haue mercy vpon them: then it was high time for him to awake out of ſleepe. The loudneſſe of the windes, and the raging of the waters, they might both togethet ſeeme to bee S. <hi>Ieromas</hi> bell, that alwayes he thought hee heard ringing in his eares, <hi>Surgite mortui, &amp; venite ad iudicium:</hi> ariſe, and come forth ſtreight way vnto Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>A terrible and fearefull ſound for vs, whoſe liues are nothing elſe, but as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinnes, ſinnes all ouer, whoſe whole liues haue beene ſubiect to the law of ſinning: and ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> calles it in the ſeuenth to the <hi>Romans:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee haue ſo inured our ſelues to ſinning, euen from our cradles, and do ſo continually endeuour our ſelues for to commit ſin, as though we were bound by law to the performance of it. Wee haue been paſt ſhame in ſinning. And as <hi>Abſolom</hi> in 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. committed his folly in the ſight of Iſrael:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.22.</note> ſo wee haue not ſticked to commit our abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2983:61"/>
at high noone, in the market-pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our ſtreetes, as though we did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make God a lyar, who calles all ſins in generall, <hi>opera tenebrarum,</hi> deeds of darkneſſe, becauſe they ſpring and come from the Prince of darkneſſe, and are rewarded in hell, a place of vtter darkneſſe. We (I ſay) by committing of them in the fight of the Sunne, doe as much as in vs lies, make them <hi>Opera lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> daily ſinnes; and therefore vnto vs, this account were very fearefull.</p>
            <p>Man (ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>) is growne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious in his ſinning, and hath ſteeled his fore-head in committing of them, ſo that hee knowes not how to bluſh when he is reproued for them. <hi>Nullus delinquendi pudor,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp; ſic pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quafi magis per ipſa peccata placeatur:</hi> we are paſt all ſhame, ſaith hee, in our finning, and ſo wee do ſtriue with our ſelues for the committing of them dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as though Almighty God were not offended with vs for them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther highly pleaſed and delighted with them.</p>
            <p>But from this kinde of ſin good Lord
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2983:61"/>
for his mercy ſake deliuer vs all, to ſinne ſo greedily, as that forthwith we ſhould take a delight and pleaſure in our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: for commonly theſe kinde of ſins, they haue annexed vnto them, <hi>duritiem cordis,</hi> a hardneſſe of heart: ſo that if God will reclaime ſuch a kinde of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, he muſt, as it is ſaid in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Math. 3.9.</note> worke it out of the very Flint, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. <hi>Ex lapidibus ſuſcitare filios Abrahae,</hi> out of ſtones he muſt raiſe vp children vnto <hi>Abraham:</hi> and this condition there is none but will grant is very dangerous.</p>
            <p>To dye in this caſe will draw a ſeuere iudgement indeed vpon man: for they ſhall be iudged with a fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe liues haue beene free from a iudgment here. Thoſe, I ſay, that haue liued here ill vpon the earth, and not made their peace with their heauenly father before they haue gone hence, all thoſe ſhall the great iudgment oppreſſe, and caſt out into vtter darkneſſe, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>But this, though it might affright vs, as who are guiltie of many tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet it could no way daunt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2983:62"/>
at all: for he was not guiltie of the leaſt thought of ſinne; neither originall ſinne, nor actual ſinne could once faſten vpon him, his conception and birth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without all ſtaine, as being concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Holy Ghoſt: his whole life it was a ſatisfaction for actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and therefore though both winde and ſeas ſhould rage neuer ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly, yet hee might ſleepe as ſecure in the middeſt of the ſtorme, as any one of vs in the greateſt calme and quiet that may be.</p>
            <p>Neither yet were the raging of the windes, or the roaring of the waters, of ſufficient authoritie to haue awaked him, had it not been the cry of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that had moued him to pitie. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Maſter, we periſh,</hi> was the Trumpet that moued him to rouze himſelfe, and take compaſſion of his forlorne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie.</p>
            <p>Their imminent danger made them pray hartily vnto their Sauiour, &amp; their feare of periſhing made them not waxe weary in their prayers, but pray vntill they awaked him to their reſcue. God
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2983:62"/>
he loues an earneſt admoniſher, and is delighted eſpecially with an importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſuiter; and therefore many times doth deny men their requeſts at the firſt, that hee might heare them more conſtant and feruent vnto him in their prayers afterwards: conſtant, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles here, who continue their intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie euen vnto death, <hi>Maſter, Maſter, wee periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſame duty of prayer it is ſo naturall, as that euen the vn-reaſonable creatures doe not omit it, but pray in their kindes, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 104.<note place="margin">Pſa. 104.21.</note> The Lyons ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hunger, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> they pray vnto the Lord, they ſeeke their meate at God. And ſo the yong Rauens, in the 147. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the Lord indeed, ſaith the Prophet feeds them, but firſt they call vpon his name: for ſo he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſa. 147.9.</note> 
               <hi>Who fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt the yong Rauens that call vpon thee.</hi> And that all excuſe may be taken away from man in this kinde, ſo that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance might not be pretended by him, it is S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> note, that <hi>qui fecit te, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cait te etiam &amp; orare:</hi> that he that at the firſt made man, and faſhioned him in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2983:63"/>
his mothers wombe, he hath taught him alſo to call vpon his name: he hath fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a praier for him himſelfe, if perhaps he ſhould be ſo dull of vnderſtanding, as not to be able to conceiue prayer of himſelfe, and commanded him to vſe it alſo. When you pray (ſaith he) ſay, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I maruaile what ſome hot ſpirits in the world will ſay to this ſame ſpeech of our Sauiours here, who would not haue his prayer vſed amongſt men, but that they ſhould pray altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the ſpirit giues them vtterance. Here I am ſure we haue Chriſts <hi>Dicite,</hi> for their <hi>ne dicite,</hi> his command againſt their prohibition. But I follow my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.7.</note>Our Sauiour in the ſeuenth Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthewes</hi> Goſpell, in three words, ſets downe the whole duetie of man in this kinde, <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Quare, Pulſa:</hi> Aske, ſaith he, ſeeke, knocke. Firſt we muſt humbly aske thoſe things that are neceſſary for vs, and yet are wanting vnto vs: for hee with-holds them to make vs more earneſt in the deſiring of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2983:63"/>
them. <hi>Deus non dat, niſi petenti, ne dee non cupienti,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> God (ſaith hee) will not giue vs any thing, vnleſſe at the firſt wee heartily begge them at our fathers hands, leſt he ſhould ſeeme to giue ſuch things as we do not eſteeme and care for, and thoſe that we ſhall aske of him, hee will giue vs in the greateſt aboundance. Let vs aske of him therefore, and bee not tongue-tyed; and aske confidently alſo, as thoſe that are ſure to receiue at his hands. And in this kinde it was a good ſpeech of <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philoſopher, who willes vs in our prayers to be confident and aſſured. <hi>Audacter,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>Deum ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga nil illum de alieno rogaturus:</hi> Aske boldly, ſaith hee, of God what thou ſtandeſt in need of, and wouldſt haue granted from his Maieſtie, aſſuring thy ſelfe of this, that whatſoeuer thou wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, he hath of his owne, and ſhall bee beholding vnto no other for the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of thee in thy requeſt. So then let vs aske of him.</p>
            <p>But yet that is not all: for if he doe not grant vs at the firſt mouing of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2983:64"/>
our ſuite, yet we muſt not waxe weary, but continue on in our courſe of prayer. And beſides our asking, a further paines is required at our hands, wee muſt bee contented to ſeeke a bleſſing for our ſelues. We muſt not onely pray, but we muſt labour alſo, and ſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teacheth vs when he ſaith, <hi>Pro quibus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum, proijs etiam &amp; laborandum eſt:</hi> For thoſe things that wee would pray vnto God for, for the ſame things wee muſt earneſtly labour: For God will not take all the paines himſelfe, and leaue vs idle in the meane time, to depend on him: and therefore it is the Apoſtles counſell in the twelfth of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.12</note> to pull vp our weake hands, that hang heauy downe, and to bow our feeble knees, which are not accuſtomed to beare our bodies weight in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and worſhip of the Lord our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</p>
            <p>Nor yet are wee at an end ſo, but hauing taken paines for to ſeeke, and by our ſearch hauing found out the right way, there remaines a doore whereby wee muſt enter, and that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2983:64"/>
doore ſtandes not open to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, come they that come will; but there wee muſt beſtow our third paines, which is to knocke, that ſo wee may get entrance at the laſt. We may ſee what paines our Sauiour CHRIST IESVS doth take for vs here: Firſt, hee intreates, and begges of vs that wee would be good vnto our ſelues. Secondly, when wee liſt not to hearken vnto his voyce, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in our old courſe of ſinning, wee haue quite loſt both the right way, and our ſelues alſo, hee ſeekes vp, and brings vs out of that Labyrinth, which we of our ſelues were neuer able to get out of: and when he hath found vs, he ſtands and knockes at the doore of euery one of our hearts, and doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be let in by vs.</p>
            <p>Conſidering then what our Sauiour doth vnto vs for our behoofe, let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke what hee againe requires at our hands: to aske feruently, to ſeeke ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, to knock forcibly at the doore of his mercie, that ſo wee may be let in to his euerlaſting kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:2983:65"/>If God then heares vs not, at the firſt knocke, we muſt not preſently be like vnto King <hi>Saul,</hi> who becauſe God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him not either by <hi>Vrim</hi> or <hi>Thummin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 28.7.</note> went ſtraightwaies from him, and asked counſell of a Witch: Wee muſt not limite God his time to come and helpe vs, but that muſt make vs knocke more violently. Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is a chiefe meanes to obtaine our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: and an example of it, our Sauiour hath left vs in the Goſpell, of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt Iudge, who though he neither fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.5.</note> nor reuerenced Man, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was importuned, he would do Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſince wee are entred in thus farre, we will goe a little further with holy <hi>Augustine,</hi> for (ſaith he) <hi>Deus non permittit ſolum, vt potas, ſed minatur eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ſi non petas:</hi> God hee does not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permit vs for to beg thoſe things that are neceſſary for vs, but he doth ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threaten vs alſo, if wee ſhall not aske of his Maieſty. Nay, aske of him, and aske of him onely, or elſe hee will bee angry with whoſoeuer ſhall not aske
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2983:65"/>
of him; as hee was with the King of Iſrael, who left him, and went to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of <hi>Beel-zebub,</hi> for the recouery of his health againe.<note place="margin">2. King. 1.3</note> 
               <hi>Is it not becauſe there is not a God in Iſrael that yee goe to inquire of Beel-zebub the God of Eckron, now therefore, thus ſaith the Lord, thou ſhalt not come downe from that bed on which thou art gon vp, but ſhalt ſurely die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our Sauiour in the 16 of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.24.</note> he was offended with his Diſciples for not asking of him: <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>yee haue asked me nothing:</hi> It ſeemes therefore that hee would haue vs aske, and when we doe aske we muſt not ceaſe our ſuites, but ſay with <hi>Iacob, Non dimittamte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.26</note> I will not let thee go, before thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed a bleſſing vpon mee: Wee muſt be inſtant vpon him as the <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anitiſh</hi> woman was for the recouery of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued daughter,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.28.</note> who would not be put off, by any anſwere our Sauiour could giue, vntill ſhee had gotten a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe for her childe: Wee muſt be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt with him, as hee to borrow bread at midnight of his friend,<note place="margin">Luke 11.8.</note> who would
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2983:66"/>
take no nay. We muſt be importunate, as the Widdow with the vniuſt Iudge, that we may ſeeme to weary him with our importunity,<note place="margin">Luke 18.5.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 18. And then we ſhall be ſure to receiue a good bleſſing from him. A good meaſure well ſhaked and heaped, and thruſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which God grant. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He aroſe,</hi> But when? Why when the Diſciples had done their vttermoſt, when they had ſhewed their humility in asking, perſeuerance in ſeeking, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity in knocking. Humility in <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> they were his ſeruants, and he their leige, Lord and Maiſter: Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in comming vnto him, <hi>They came vnto him:</hi> Importunity, <hi>we periſh: And they came vnto him ſaying, Maiſter Maiſter we periſh,</hi> and by this importunity of theirs, they obtained their requeſt, <hi>Then he aroſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do not reade in this ſame Story, nor in any other of the Euangeliſts that do record it, that either the Apoſtles, or Diſciples of our Sauiour, tooke any other courſe, for the ſafe-gard of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and of their liues (though moſt
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2983:66"/>
of them were Fiſhermen, and therefore knew better how to beſtirre themſelues in a ſtorme then Land men do) but onely prayer; no labour is mentioned, ſaue onely their paines of comming vnto him, and the reaſon of it is plaine: Art is paſt, when Nature is let looſe, when both windes and ſeas haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their bounds, then they knew their beſt recourſe was to their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for humane labour was all but vaine.</p>
            <p>And hearty prayer, we know, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reckoned the firſt and the laſt helpe of the godly man:<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.21</note> ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> in their perſons, ſaith, <hi>In nomine ſancto eius, ſperanimus,</hi> we haue truſted in his holy name, and God hath bene their great deliuerer.</p>
            <p>But yet ſo farre forth we muſt relye vpon the Lord, as we our ſelues withall be not wanting vnto our ſelues, while hope remaines. For, for to ſet our ſelues downe, and lay all vpon the Diuine Prouidence, is iuſt the lazy knaue in <hi>Iſidor,</hi> who when his Cart was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, would needs haue his God
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2983:67"/>
               <hi>Hercules</hi> to come downe from heauen, and raiſe it vp againe, whilſt he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would bee a ſpectator of it, and ſit by and giue aime. Whilſt there is meanes left wee muſt bee content, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with our prayers, for to vſe them lawfully, and when all earthly law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes faile, and forſake vs, then wee muſt flye wholy vnto Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>Reaſon teacheth vs thus much, that when wee may hope to finde a ſpring then we muſt alſo beſtow our paines in digging for it: And when the ſoyle will beare corne, then we muſt vſe our skill and labour in tilling of it. When <hi>Eliſha</hi> was in a little Village, not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him from the <hi>Aſſirians</hi> power, hee had horſes and Chariots of fire round about him, to defend him from their force, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6. but when he was in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> a Towne of Gariſon,<note place="margin">2. King. 6.17.</note> then when the King of Iſrael ſent to fetch his head, hee ſaid to thoſe that were with him, ſhut the dore, as it is in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 32. verſe. So our Sauiour Chriſt in the wilderneſſe miraculouſly fed whole
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2983:67"/>
multitudes, that came vnto him: But when he was in the Citie againe, he ſent his Diſciples forth for to buy their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary prouiſion.<note place="margin">Iohn 4.8.</note> So we muſt all labour whilſt there is any hope, and when hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane helpe faileth, then flie vnto the protection of the Almighty: So we ſee prayer it is the firſt and the laſt helpe of the righteous man, to beginne with God and to end in him.</p>
            <p>The wicked ſinner, he would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be the righteous mans Ape, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him in this duety of his, but that ſhall not be at the firſt entrance into his buſineſſe, but at the laſt gaſpe of his life, when they lie howling vpon their beds, ſaith the Prophet <hi>Hoſ.</hi> in his 7. chapter,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.14.</note> and yet all is but in apiſh imitation nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for their heart, euen then, is farre from the Lord, as it is in the ſame Verſe of the ſame Chapter: They haue not cried vnto mee, ſaith the Lord, with their hearts, when they how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon their beds, and therefore as their hearts in their extremities, were farre from God, ſo was hee farre alſo from their deliuerance. Theſe heere
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2983:68"/>
with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> they cryed, <hi>De profundis,</hi> out of the deepe vnto him, out of the deepe of the waters, but more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out of the deepe and bottome of their hearts, and therefore obtained pardon for all their liues.</p>
            <p>The mouth, here perhaps amongſt men, may make a ſhew of Religion, and the hand glory in oſtentation of the giftes that it hath giuen, but yet the heart is the iewel which the Lord looks after. There may be hypocriſie in the mouth that ſpeakes, and vaine-glory in the hand that giues, but if the heart bee vpright and entire, that is an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice vnto the Lord: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, by <hi>Salomon,</hi> asketh nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the mouth nor the hand, but the heart;<note place="margin">Pro. 23.26.</note> 
               <hi>Fili da mihi cor:</hi> My ſonne giue me thy heart. As thou giueſt as much as the Lord requireth, if thou giue him thy heart; ſo if thou giueſt all that thou haſt, and keepeſt thy heart backe from him, thou giueſt nothing at all, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, or will vouchſafe to accept from thee. The Apoſtles cry here, it came from the heart, from the bottome of the heart,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2983:68"/>
Maiſter, Maiſter we periſh, and by that they obtained pardon for their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: then he aroſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Then hee aroſe: Hee could haue riſen ſooner; had it pleaſed him, but he would not, hee would firſt haue them to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate vnto him, and then hee would ariſe. <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> tels vs of ſome mighty men, that are much in this vaine, they haue <hi>aures in pedibus,</hi> their eares in the ſoles of their feete; can heare none ſpeake but ſuch as he ſuppliant at their foote for mercy; but that is out of their pride and arrogancy, who wil be known to be in place and authority ouer their brethren. Thoſe they are of <hi>Caines</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, who built him a Citty, <hi>Vt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaretur in ea;</hi> that he might dominere in it, ſo theſe they get them aloft that the Golden Calfe may be adored: But this of our Sauiours here, it was farre otherwiſe, it was their duties all to fall proſtrate, before his Maieſty, and then he knew, it was his part to helpe them <hi>Then he aroſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſleepe as it was voluntary vnto him, in this place, as heretofore I haue
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2983:69"/>
told you, he could ſleepe when hee liſt, and watch as long as he liſt, and yet no preiudice vnto his nature: So he could riſe alſo when himſelfe pleaſed from ſleepe againe. As his death was volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, &amp; from himſelfe, <hi>oblatus eſt quia vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit,</hi> hee was offred vp vnto death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe himſelfe would dye; and ſo much he profeſſeth of himſelfe in the tenth of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.18.</note> 
               <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>taketh my life from me, but I lay it downe of my ſelfe:</hi> So here, <hi>dorminit quia voluit:</hi> hee ſlept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would ſleepe, and when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him he could awake againe.</p>
            <p>This then it may be a leſſon for head-ſtrong man, not to be his owne caruer in his buſineſſe, and appoint God his time, when to rouze himſelfe: for he knowes his time better then man can appoynt it to him; but with patience he muſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe his ſoule, and when he ſees what is conuenient for him, then he will rouze himſelfe to his deliuery. Indeed the ſhip in the meane time may labour &amp; roule, the wind ſtorme and blow, the ſeas rage and ſwell; yet without Gods good will and pleaſure, not any one haire of their
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2983:69"/>
heads ſhal periſh. <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, we make no queſtion, was tumbled and toſſed in thoſe mighty waters, but wee doe not reade that either it was ſunke or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.<note place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>Rebecca</hi> ſhee was pulled and pained, and euen rent in ſunder, by the contention of her babes within her wombe, but yet ſhe ſuffered no abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.24.</note> The houſe founded vpon a Rocke it ſuffered both the violence of the ſtorme, and the rage of the waters, and yet it was not ouerthrowne. The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.22</note> ſhe was perſecuted by the red Dragon, and followed by him from place to place, but ſhe was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of her fearefull aduerſary. So wee, if wee ſhall reſt our ſelues in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and refer all to the gouernment of God, Hee in His good time will deliuer vs out of all our troubles, he will as hee did heere vnto the Apoſtles, raiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vp to our defence, <hi>Then he aroſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And rebuked the winde and the raging of the water, and they ceaſed, and there was a calme.</hi> Now are wee come to the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent demonſtration of our Sauiours Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:2983:70"/>In the former parts of the Text, wee ſaw him as a meere naturall Man, meeke and gentle, not ſtriuing for ſuperiority, or deſirous to command: Hee enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Ship with his Diſciples, and being entred laies himſelfe downe, for his reſt and quiet; Hee opens not his mouth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to controule his owne company, or any other that were in the ſhip.</p>
            <p>So was His whole life, meeke and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; in his birth, ſaith S. <hi>Ber. Parua lans, quia parui laus,</hi> there was but litle praiſe, becauſe it was but the praiſe of a little One,<note place="margin">Eſay 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Vnto vs a child is born;</hi> there his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty is not extolled, but yet his humility is aboue all we are able to ſpeake, to be commended.</p>
            <p>Exceedingly to bee commended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of vs, eſpecially if wee ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Him as hee hath deſerued of euery one of vs. For Him that S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw in his owne nature, the knowledge and wiſedome of God himſelfe: Him for our ſakes, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaw leſſened below the Angels: Him that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw ſitting on the Throne, and thouſand thouſands miniſtring before Him: Him
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:2983:70"/>
the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaw againe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon earth with wretched man: Him that <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw the Lord of Hoſts: Him the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaw in ſhape like a Leaper, meeke and humble, and all for our benefite, and therefore aboue all to bee commended of vs.</p>
            <p>And in this gentle faſhion, not being prouoked by vs, who hath deſerued ſo much good at our hands, He comes nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt vnto his owne Diuine Nature and Eſſence; For God in his owne Nature and Eſſence is milde and gentle, and if he be not ouermuch prouoked, will not break forth into rage and fury. The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that were of a fiery Spirit, they were moſt vnlike, and contrary to their Maſter, for hee does not delight in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe hurtfull fires: Hee is called the <hi>Day-ſtar,</hi> to inlighten,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 3.8.</note> not the <hi>Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar</hi> to ſcorch and burn. And God is ſaid for to haue walked in the Coole of the day, not in the Heate of the day; and as it were alſo, to haue fetched many turnes, thereby to coole himſelfe, before he would call his aduerſary to account: And when he would ſpeake vnto <hi>Eliah,</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:2983:71"/>
Hee ſhewed himſelfe neither in the ſtrong wind,<note place="margin">2. Kings 19.12.</note> nor in the earth-quake, nor yet in the fire, but in a ſmall ſtill voyce: And all this to teach me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what their duty is to do, to be kind and mercifull as their heauenly Father of Himſelfe is merciful; and ſo the Saints in former times haue profeſſed of themſelues. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayes of himſelfe that he was like vnto a weaned childe: <hi>Iacob</hi> compares himſelfe vnto a worme: Our Sauiour, his Diſciples vnto little Children: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would haue his <hi>Corinthians</hi> meeke and gentle, forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing each other, as God for Chriſts ſake had forgiuen them. In a word, as God himſelfe forgiuing our iniquities, and pardoning all our ſinnes; Hee hitherto was meeke and gentle, but now <hi>Increpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit ventis,</hi> He rebuked the wind and the raging of the waters, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He rebuked the wind:</hi> Why the wind wee all know is a lawleſſe creature, and will not be kept vnder, and ſo our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſpeakes of it, where he ſaith, <hi>ſpiritus ſpirat vbi vult,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>The winde bloweth where it liſteth, and who is hee that ſhall controule it?</hi> True indeed, who is he that
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:2983:71"/>
can controule it, if hee be but onely man: but if the wind ſhall be ouer-bold and ſaucy with his Lord and Maker, and exceed the bounds and limits that hee hath appointed it, it ſhall haue his due checke as well as any other of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>He rebuked the winds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how did he rebuke them, may ſome man aske? What, did he ſend his letters of defiance vnto the windes, as <hi>Xerxes</hi> did when they croſſed his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments? Or did he cauſe fetters and ſhackles to be caſt into the water, as the ſame <hi>Xerxes</hi> did, and make it take the Baſtinado, when the angry <hi>Helleſpont</hi> would not grant him paſſage for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and Souldiers? How did hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke them? Why, how ſhould hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke them but by his Word? For Hee that made the windes, and ſent them out by his Word, by his Word alſo was able to countermand them, when it pleaſed him.</p>
            <p>The Heathen Poets fancied to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a God of the winds, <hi>Aeolus,</hi> who in a Caue kept them all together, and as hee was either pleaſed, or diſpleaſed
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:2983:72"/>
with Mankinde, ſo he let them out and called them in againe, either for their profite, or to wreake his anger and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure on them: But Chriſt the onely true <hi>Aeolus,</hi> does not let them out to range at their owne pleaſure, but when they are forth he rules them as he liſts: ſo the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> tels vs <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104. <hi>Who laieth the beames of his Chambers in the waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 104.3.</note> 
               <hi>and maketh the Clouds his Chariot, and walketh vpon the wings of the wind:</hi> Both winds and waters then, are at his command, and as it pleaſeth him he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces them forwards or keeps them backe, for the benefite of his.</p>
            <p>The company of the righteous, they are Gods eſpeciall care that hee lookes after, &amp; ſo much the Poet doth reueale: <hi>Cura Deûm dî ſunt &amp; qui coluere, colan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> and therefore rather then they ſhall take any harme, hee will bee preſent to worke a miracle for their reliefe: he will rebuke both the winds and the waters, &amp; make them calme, &amp; al for their ſakes. To work miracles, now adaies amongſt vs, though it may ſeeme ſtrange vnto vs, becauſe it is a commanding of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:2983:72"/>
againſt the courſe of nature, as to cauſe the wind to ceaſe with a word, &amp; to quiet the Seas onely with a becke, be beyond humane conceipt, yet with God for his Elect ſake, they are as <hi>Philo Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſpeakes, but <hi>Iudicra,</hi> meere toyes, and trifles; nay, he will do greater matters then theſe for ſuch as be his: he will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the Sea for his ſeruants to goe through, and drowne his enemies that follow after: Hee will raine down bread and fleſh from heauen for them, in a time of dearth, when the earth will not affoord it them: Hee will bring water out of the hard Rocke, when they ſhall be in a barren and dry ground, where no water is; Out of very ſtones, to raiſe vp children vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> is eaſy and at hand with him to do.</p>
            <p>And if any man ſhall aske mee the reaſon of theſe ſo great and miraculous workes of his, I anſwere ſuddainely againe with S. <hi>Auguſt. Bonitas &amp; gratia Dei,</hi> the mercy and loue of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with from all eternity hee hath loued his Elect, hath prouoked him to doe them all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:2983:73"/>Let vs then all, as many as profeſſe our ſelues to belong to him, magnifie this great God for this extraordinary goodneſſe of his: and as we weare the badges of Chriſt Ieſus on our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, ſo let vs faithfully adore him in our hearts; and then though dangers threaten, and ſtormes ariſe, yet there ſhall appeare at the laſt a quiet calme, a calme and quietneſſe of conſcience here, and an eternall calme in the world to come. The which quietneſſe both here and there, that we all may be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of, Hee grant vs that here cauſed this calme to his Apoſtles, Chriſt Ieſus the righteous, to whom with the Father and the holy Spirit, three Perſons, and one Eternall, Almighty, and Euerliuing God, be all Praiſe, Honour, and Glory, this day and for euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 2. line 9. for good, reade God, p. 16 l. 24. <hi>mementate</hi> r. <hi>mementote:</hi> p. 22. l. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 29. l. 20. <hi>quae</hi> r. <hi>qua:</hi> l. <hi>ead. quae</hi> r. <hi>qua.</hi> p. 35. l. 3. <hi>fugero</hi> r. <hi>fugere:</hi> p. <hi>ead.</hi> l. 27. to r. two: p. 36. l. 24. loather r. loatheſt: p. 57. ſ. 2. <hi>ſummum</hi> r. <hi>ſummam:</hi> p. 59. l. 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 63. l. 2. iife r. life to. p. 97. l. 26. whole r. whale.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
